If you correctly predict all the results
in the European Football Championship,
- I'll give you five quid.
- Five quid? If I predict the scores?
Just to win or draw.
What are the odds on that?
In that case, Kevin, I'll bet you 50 quid.
- I'll make it £50,000.
- All right, then I'll raise you.
- £50 million.
- £50 million, Gary?
That's as much we give the EU every day.
It's your chance to win it, Kev.
- You can finally buy that Picasso.
- My favourite artist, Gary.
And your chance, too.
It's free to enter.
Just fill in the form at 50million.uk
and if you correctly predict all the outcomes
from the European Football Championship this summer,
you could win £50 million.
Go to 50million.uk now
and you could win £50 million.
You just log on to 50million.uk,
click "sign up",
then you pick which team wins
or whether it's a draw for each game, and that's it. Good luck.
Gary, Turkey or Albania?
- Well, they're both joining the EU, aren't they?
- Yes, I know,
but which one do you think will win?
Well, Turkey's got 76 million people,
- so they should have a good team.
- Turkey it is, then, Gary.
Fancy some quinoa?
Quinoa? I think you mean "keen-wah", Gary.
I think I prefer chips.
Hey! Fancy a kickabout?
Gary, mind the late-19th-century paintings.
We're multimillionaires now, Kev.
Did you know a Member of the European Parliament gets paid
- £75,000 a year?
- How much?
And 45 grand expenses.
Get out. I heard they get 300-euro-a-day expenses
just for turning up.
Hey, Gazza, we should have been MEPs.
Stroke of luck we won that 50 million, eh, Kev?
I wonder who's doing our jobs now.
Probably someone charging half the price.
Lucky we got out when we did.
THEY LAUGH THEN SIGH
MUSIC PLAYS
SHE COUGHS
MUSIC CONTINUES, SPEECH INAUDIBLE