This is Sam. He's 14 months old.
How you vote in the European Referendum will shape his future
and the future of everyone in our country.
If we remain in Europe,
there'll be more opportunities for our children
to follow their dreams and make the most out of life
because being in Europe helps our businesses grow
and create jobs, giving young people the chance to learn a trade,
get into work and get on in life.
People setting up a new business
can trade freely with customers across Europe,
helping them build something of their own
and create jobs for others.
Companies from around the world set up factories and offices here
so that they can do business throughout Europe,
meaning more opportunities for Sam and everyone in our country.
And when you're at work, your rights are secured by EU legislation -
paid holiday and sick leave, equal rights,
maternity and paternity leave -
all protected by EU law.
Being in Europe also means families enjoy lower prices
in our shops and supermarkets.
This saves an average household £350 a year so as Sam grows older,
he'll have more money to put aside for a deposit on a home
or a car or a holiday with his family.
Remaining in Europe will keep our economy stronger
so we can invest more in vital services
like schools and the NHS and it means Sam and all of us
have the freedom to travel, study,
work and live wherever we want across the EU.
And Sam and every child in our country will grow up in a Britain
that leads in the world, that works with others to tackle the big issues
like climate change and terrorism.
But leaving the EU would mean losing all of this.
It's a leap in the dark and would leave UK families £4,300 worse off.
So, on June 23rd, vote for more opportunities
and a stronger future for Sam and everyone you know -
your family and friends, your children and grandchildren.
Vote for a Britain that's stronger, safer and better off.