At the end of the war, Britain created the NHS.
It protects us throughout our lives.
But it's in danger. You can help it.
Every week we send ?350 million to Brussels.
Money that's wasted.
That's enough to build a new hospital every week.
It will get worse.
The euro is broken, and the EU plans to let in another five countries.
Imagine what will happen when you're paying for the euro bailouts.
Imagine what will happen to public services
when Albania, Macedonia, Montenegro, Serbia and Turkey join the EU.
Imagine our money being spent on our priorities.
You can make this happen. This might be our last chance.
So, vote leave on 23rd June.
Let's take back control.
MUSIC PLAYS
SHE COUGHS
MUSIC PLAYS, SPEECH INAUDIBLE
At the end of the war, Britain created the NHS.
It protects us throughout our lives.
But it's in danger. You can help it.
Every week we send ?350 million to Brussels.
Money that's wasted.
That's enough to build a new hospital every week.
It will get worse.
The euro is broken. And the EU plans to let in another five countries.
Imagine what will happen when you are paying for the Euro bailouts.
Imagine what will happen to public services
when Albania, Macedonia, Montenegro, Serbia and Turkey join the EU.
Imagine our money being spent on our priorities.
You can make this happen.
This might be our last chance.
So, vote leave on 23rd June.
Let's take back control.
To find out more of the facts, go to voteleave.uk.