The brutal killing of MP Jo Cox has shocked the nation and paused
the referendum debate, just days before voting.
Had we become, on all sides, simply too angry
This morning, the big question about our national future returns,
with perhaps, we'll see, a rather different tone.
My guests today include the Labour leader, Jeremy Corbyn,
and the joint leader of the Leave campaign, the Justice
Two more politicians in our papers review this morning -
Conservative Remainer and unlikely king of Twitter Sir Nicholas Soames.
And the leading Out campaigner Labour's Kate Hoey.
And we're joined too by the Sun's star columnist Jane Moore.
Plus, music from one of the hottest young stars in Britain,
But first, the news, with Steph McGovern.
Two special church services will be held at Birstall in West Yorkshire
this morning to remember the local MP Jo Cox,
Thomas Mair, who is accused of her murder, appeared
in court in London yesterday and was remanded in custody.
He will appear at the Old Bailey tomorrow.
A day of remembrance ahead for this village in West Yorkshire.
Three days after the killing of the Labour MP Jo Cox,
campaigning in the EU referendum has started up again.
The Justice Secretary, Michael Gove, who wants to leave,
insists Britain could be a "progressive beacon"
David Cameron has urged voters to reject Nigel Farage's vision
for the country which, he claimed, would "divide rather than unite".
Health unions have written to David Cameron urging him not
to scrap nursing and midwifery bursaries in England.
The Government says that replacing grants with student loans
will provide funding for many more training places.
But the Royal College of Nursing says that the plans would be
a "reckless gamble" with the future of the NHS workforce.
A day of remembrance ahead for this village in West Yorkshire.
Later this morning, church services will
be held and a book of condolences opened for those who wish to
to pay their respects for Jo Cox, who was killed on Thursday, as she
made her way here, to her constituency surgery.
Yesterday, the MP's family, surrounded by the
people of Birstall, came to the place where she was attacked.
Her sister, Kim Leadbeater, said Jo would never
She will live on through all the good people in the world.
Through Brendan, through us, and through her
truly wonderful children, who will always know what an utterly
She was a human being and she was perfect.
People have been reacting to the 41-year-old's death across
A fund set up in her name has already raised hundreds of thousands
Meanwhile, yesterday, the man accused of killing the MP,
When asked his name, he replied, "death to
He is also charged with grievous bodily
harm against a 77-year-old man who came to her aid
The 52-year-old was remanded in custody and will appear
There have been disturbances in the Turkish city of Istanbul,
following an attack on fans of the British rock band Radiohead.
Police used tear gas to disperse hundreds of people protesting
The fans, who had gathered at a music store to listen
to the band's latest album, were reportedly targeted
for drinking alcohol and playing music during Ramadan.
Those words by the murdered MP's sister, she was perfect, dominate
some of the papers. Because of legal problems, cannot talk much about
this, so you will have to forgive us. This one, like a lot of the
Sunday papers, finally make up -- makes up its mind on Europe. The
Sunday Times, slightly hedging its bets, you might think, with David,
talking about the dangers of leaving. Michael Gove has given
interviews in lots of the papers, and we will be talking to him later
on. And there's Jo Cox's parents- we know there are some some evil people
in this world, but there are an awful lot of good people, too. .
Looking at the opinion polls, this does in deed appear to be the case,
Britain split down the middle. You met Jo Cox a few times? Only
slightly. I met her as a colleague, really, in the lobbies. And I think
Kate was in the same position. We knew her as a new member of
Parliament. I was most impressed by her ability to work across the
issues, cross-party, like Kate and I have done on immigration and other
matters. If you want to get anything done in the House of Commons, you
have to work cross-party, and she was a doer. I loved the story by
Andrew Mitchell, in the Telegraph, saying that he took her to talk to
the Russian ambassador, to talk about Syria, and she gave the
Russian ambassador what for and he was doubly chastened. And he is a
tough guy. Yes, and she gave him what for. I am very taken by the
last article she wrote, which the Mail on Sunday reprints today in
which she talks very eloquently about the Remain campaign. That was
the context in which I met her. We were both members of the cross-party
Remain campaign. I think she writes very powerfully and knowledgeably
about the migrants and the need to curb migrants, but also to do it in
a sensible and humane way. And of course her husband has pick up the
torch and is tweeting and writing everywhere as well. What was
remarkable, having only been a member of Parliament for such a
short time, she was so well-known for the causes that she was working
cross-party on. And I think also, what has come through very much, and
I think all MPs will be so touched by that, the effect within her own
constituency of her own constituents and the help that she had given
them. It is one area of MPs' lives which can get ignored by the media,
that day today, we are all doing I think pretty good work. But she
particularly seems to have done that in that short time. She was from the
area, it was her home area. I think the papers have all done some
wonderful tributes to her. It is interesting, Sir Nicholas was saying
that she was a cross-party kind of MP. And she has got cross-party
tributes, from right across the press. Absolutely. As you just said,
she was perfect. It is the whole thing off, she was a human being.
How her sister stood up and made that speech, all credit to her.
Absolutely incredible. You just look at what happens when somebody... It
is about their parents, their siblings, their children. But as you
rightly say, Kate, the constituents. And these pictures of the sea of
flowers, and when she was first killed, the reporters, who normally
they do vox pops of people on the streets, people were actually
crying. And they all had personal stories of how she had helped them.
People think Westminster is full of career politicians who have no...
There is a lot of abuse of politicians. And I think Jo Cox and
her tragic story has highlighted that there are a lot of on the
ground MPs, doing the job as it should be done. Sir Nicholas, have
you noticed an additional aggression in recent years towards MPs, and how
do you deal with it? You need want to go out and meet your
constituents, you do not want to be surrounded by police or whatever. We
shall go on with our surgeries as we have always done. Nevertheless, I
think it is an important point - the job of the MP in the constituency is
to be round and about, and constantly so. Despite what you
would think, MPs are astonishingly accessible, at any time. But it has
changed, the public debate has coarsened, and there are a whole lot
of events which led up to that. It is now much rougher than it was. It
has always been a rough trade, Dubai to Hogarth. But it is now much more
vicious. Particularly so, for women. There was something in the Telegraph
yesterday listing the threats, and rape threats, made against women MPs
on all sides. Yes, and that is a result of social media, because it
is so instant. Somebody says something, and everybody else joins
in. Personally I just ignore things which come through, unless it is
something which is really, really threatening. Not just women MPs, TV
presenters, journalists... Anyone in public life. Look at the way our
nurses, our schoolteachers, I sometimes threatened. It is a
general coarsening of the public... In the Sunday Telegraph, James
Kirchhoff saying that this is going to divide the country further, he
thinks. Well, he's trying to move on from that, saying there will be a
lot of people for different reasons trying to link this with the
referendum. And I think this piece by James Kirkup is saying that it is
very, very important what happens after Thursday, that the tone of the
debate is kept in a way that people will not afterwards be able to work
together. He says the one certainty about the political consequences of
Jo Cox's awful death, the more it is linked into the referendum debate
are the harder it will be for people divided by that referendum to come
back together afterwards. I think that is really important. It is all
about tone? It is, and about people respecting other people's views,
even if they do not like them. Sir Nicholas, talking of which, Michael
Gove and yourself do not exactly share the same views as you on the
EU, but here's one of the most courteous men in British politics.
He is also a great friend, and I have great respect for him. There
are very profound views on both sides of this argument, that's why
it is so difficult for people to come to a conclusion. I take issue
only with his... He has written an interview in the Telegraph today,
Michael Gove, in which he says that a post-Brexit return you would be a
beacon of light. Well, I think Britain is a beacon of light
already. I think it is a begin of light, hope, internationalism and
diversity. I think people have always wanted to come here and they
always will. I don't think this is something related to Brexit or
non-Brexit. I think Britain has been a beacon of hope for generations. I
hope that when people make their minds up, they will consider that it
is a finely balanced argument, but it is not a new argument. You get
people saying to you that you are dishonouring the memory of your
grandfather, Sir Winston Churchill, by staying on the soccer lick side.
Have you found it pretty heated? I have found it very heated. People
say, your grandfather would be turning in his grave. How on earth
do they know? It is 50 years since he died. He started his public life
charging on a horse with a sword and ended up as Prime Minister ushering
in the nuclear age. It was likely that his views changed very
substantially over that period of time, and between then and now, I
cannot believe that he would not have a very different view possibly
on what he thought 80 years ago on the potential European Union. So it
is very difficult to say. On the other side of the argument, we have
got David Cameron, and object, self-imposed human nation awaits...?
Yes, but actually... I think, to be fair, he probably did not write the
headline! Following on from what Nicholas said, the language is so
important. He has said all the usual things which he has been saying. But
I picked out that he said, there is not one credible voice which it says
Britain, I think he means the United Kingdom, would be better off for
opting to leave the United Kingdom. Is he really saying that those four
or five members of his Cabinet, who are talking about how we could do so
well outside the EU, and how it would be much more democratic, is he
saying that they are not credible? I think this is a last-gasp attempt by
the Prime Minister, in a language, I have to say, much less strident than
he has been doing recently... The language is changing. The language
is changing, but here still wrong. He is referring to the Governor of
the Bank of England, the IMF, and that these views cannot be
dismissed. I am in a perfect position on this sofa. We have an
authentic ditherer. I am! I read an article which says we should remain,
and I go, yes! And then I read an article... I got hundreds of e-mails
from people saying, they are also undecided. We never talk about the
don't knows. But there's million is of you. I think there's lots of
bashful Brexit is! This is Donald Trump. He has given
an interview to the Sunday Times. He has said he will talk to him and
Putin, you will talk to them all. Everything he is asked, I think he
has had media training. He has become very measured and not
pejorative at all. Asked about the view of David Cameron where he said
he was divisive, stupid and wrong in saying he was going to ban all
Muslims from coming into America. His reply was, I respect David
Cameron. He does not know me. I respect what he has done and what he
is doing. I imagine I would have a very good relationship with him if I
were successful. Sir Nicolas Adams has been looking at China Daily on
his iPad. -- Sir Nicolas Soames. There was an interview. He became a
Member of Parliament in 1976. He has been around the track on all sorts
of occasions. He is a staunch, pro-European supporter of great
experience. In his piece to the china Daily come he is talking that
the complexities of trade with China and the point that, whatever one
says of the rights and wrongs in this argument, putting together a
trade deal with anyone is not easy. Making the point that to put a trade
deal with Britain alone with China will be very complicated. The
notable point is he has finally announced he is going and that will
be a big loss to Parliament. A big, clever, experienced man. Let's talk
about another clever and experienced man, Tim Peake, who has fallen to
earth. If you had spent the amount of time in space he had, it eat in
air dried food with boiling water poured on them, what would you crave
most? The me, it will be a juicy steak with a glass of red wine.
Apparently he has been craving pizza. And a beer. I'm with him on
the nice, cold beer that not the pizza. Earlier, this morning, I told
the man who had been on the shuttle, an American spacemen. He had been
dreaming about eating salad. That really is not much to look forward
to. I love that he landed in the first thing he said, which was
really charming, the fresh air. Smelling the flowers and the fresh
air. After being six months in a space craft, it must be an
extraordinary moment. The effect of gravity wearing off must be quite a
thing and he is on the way back to see his family now. He has got back
just on time for Father's Day. There is a short article in the Sunday
express written by Prince William, the Duke of Cambridge. He is talking
about celebrating his third Father's Day as a dad. It is an interesting
article because he talks quite strongly against. It shows his real
determination to keep pushing the whole question of mental health and
the idea, the importance of having more resources into that whole area.
That will strike a chord with a lot of people. He is also pointing out
that dad is a very important. For some young men I see in my
constituency, sometimes young men feel devalued. They feel no one
really is interested in them. Sarah Baxter, rather movingly in the
Sunday Times. It is a fantastic piece which is quite curious. She
starts off by saying he was not around much because my parents split
up when I was nine and his job as a pilot took him away. She doesn't go
one to say... He had a belief in hand, that was the point. Her mother
played a very strong roll as well. I did not have a father figure in my
life. Single parents of either gender can do both. My husband has a
very strong relationship with our children and I do think, you know,
fathers are very, very important. The son of Leonard Cohen was saying,
what he valued about his father was he made a very good tuna salad. I
hope when I go, my kids will say, he made quite a good salad. Two
mentions of salad in the paper review. He would have thought? Are
you going to get a monstrous cake? If my children remember. After all
the publicity there has been, I hope they will. Thanks to you all.
Lovely this morning but what a grim old summer it's been so far.
I'm just a simple soul, who sits here patiently week after week
waiting for Peter Gibbs to bring me some happy news.
If you do not have any good news, make it up.
The sun is shining at the moment across the east of Scotland. A
beautiful start to the day. It will not last. Rain clouds are gathering
in the West. The rain is beginning to moving across Northern Ireland
and it will spread into Scotland, Wales and the western side of
England by the afternoon. It means we hang on to a bit of sunshine. The
easternmost counties of England in particular. Much warmer than
yesterday, up to 21, 22 in Norfolk. The high teens at best weather wind
and rain is piling in further west. The rain will continue to march
eastwards overnight so we will see a spell of wet weather. It will be a
fairly mild night with temperatures no lower than 14, 15 degrees. A bit
of a wet start to be Day across the southern half of England and Wales a
wet journey to work in many places. Sunny spells and showers following
on behind. There are signs that through the middle part of the week
we could see warmer, more humid air from the near continent. That could
well produce thundery showers. That probably will not meet your exacting
standards. The death of Jo Cox united
politicians in grief, and there will be tributes
to her from all sides But the paused referendum campaign
is getting back How will it be conducted over these
final few days? I'm joined now by the Labour
leader, Jeremy Corbyn. Before we start, you obviously knew
Tempra Ais a colleague. Any particular memories? -- Jo as a
colleague. She was passionate about Batley and spend. She grew up in
that area. I was there on Friday for a vigil. Biting memories in the
condolence book in the church. -- writing memories. They were totally
shocked and in grief for what happened. This was a murder of her
but it was also an attack on democracy and an attack on the right
of somebody to be represented to elect you and to go about their
business. We should also think for a moment of the two people who
intervened to try to help her. One of them is still in hospital, a
retired miner who tried to protect her. He will be out soon, we hope.
We have lost a great talent, someone who spoke up in Parliament for human
rights, peace in Syria and so many other places. People talk a lot of
the time about MPs. She was rooted in that place. She was one of
theirs. The whole point of democracy and involvement, when you elect
someone to a council, Member of Parliament but if you are to do your
job, you cannot leave the area of the people or the place that you
there. If we move our MPs into some sort of hermetically sealed
container where they are shipped from place to place, then we lose
everything. I love my constituency. I love my community. What I love is
just walking about, chatting to people, many of whom I have known
for many years. That way you pick up the reality of legislation, the
reality in our case of austerity and the poverty that goes with it.
You're better informed to do your job. If you are in some kind of
security bubble, you very rapidly lose all of that and we have to
defend that and we have to defend people against this kind of
appalling attack that took place. It is not the first time. Other MPs
have been assaulted. Stephen Timms was assaulted, George Galloway was
assaulted. A number of others have been assaulted. Ian Gow was killed
in 1990. Were you aware of the growing worry of physical attacks?
The Shadow Leader of the house said he thought eventually somebody would
be killed. We have talked about this and the levels of security that MPs
need and want. There is a degree of fon ability. If you have an open
office and an open advice bureau, which is what we all want to do. We
want to see everyone, no matter how difficult their lives are. We do not
want to be cut off from them. At the same time we need security of some
sort to protect people. It is not just for MPs, it is for everyone.
MPs just protecting themselves is of course essential and important as
tragically the death of Jo showed. Everyone else needs to be protected
against any kind of attack, whatever the appalling motive might be behind
the attack. UN the Prime Minister were standing shoulder to shoulder.
-- you and the Prime Minister. When the House of Commons regroups
tomorrow, they have had comments that the parties should mingle and
sit on each other's benches. We are thinking about that. Tomorrow will
be a dignified occasion, not a time for lots of long speeches. It is
about all MPs standing together. An MP has died. It is an attack on all
of us. We have to reach out. Do you think the recent political
atmosphere, the referendum or anything else can has created a more
anti-MP mood? I do. I think MPs are perceived to be cut off. In reality,
most are not. Decision-making is seen to be cut off and the lives of
so many people, where they face housing problems, insecurity at
work, falling living standards, problems where children do not get
any housing, all of those issues to make people feel, hang on, what is
the political situation ever doing for me? Reducing working conditions
are making life more difficult for people creates a sense of anger and
insecurity. What is the answer? Is the answer to kick out all get
together and do something different? One thing that is going on, if we
vote to leave the EU, part of the story behind that will be lots and
lots of traditional Labour voters not listening to you or the party
leadership on immigration are going in the direction of Ukip on
immigration. Do you accept that in some sense the party has lost the
day of a lot of your traditional, white working-class constituents? We
have had several years of endless newspaper headlines blaming
everything on migration without ever being prepared to look at the
guarantee of the expectation of people in this country and across
Europe. The Mike Ashley story, sports direct, Dennis Skinner made a
brilliant comment, when it was a pit, people from all over Europe
were working there as minors. The same conditions, the same housing,
the same union. Now there are several other people working on zero
hours contracts who have been shipped in from elsewhere. The
answer to that is not to blame them, the answer is, guess, at one level
to blame Mike Ashley but to blame the lack of regulation of working
conditions both here and in other parts of Europe. The workers
directive is very important. Do you think immigration should not be an
issue? There are a lot of people really, really worried about the
effects on school places, housing and public services and wage
compression. The reality is more than 2 million British people live
in Europe. Quite a lot of people from the European Union, mainly
Poland, have made their homes in Britain and are working, paying
taxes and all of that. The issues surely have to be to improve working
conditions, improved protection is all across Europe and look at those
who are making a great deal of money out of this exploitation. I mention
the posting of workers directive, it also about local wages and
conditions. If everybody had to be paid the relevant local rate, things
would be different. A number of people coming to the country would
probably be reduced. Do you think worries about immigration would
reduce? I do. There has to be the reintroduction of the migrant impact
fund which was introduced in 2008, which was a special payment that
will go to local authorities where there have been big changes. In the
same way that in the 1960s, the then Labour government introduced the
Commonwealth immigration fund for the same purpose. Some groups feel
they have been adversely affected. They will get more help for schools,
hospital places and so on. Absolutely. It brings people
together, to achieve a better society for all and recognise that
we have a lot of young people studying and working in Europe, we
have a lot of young Europeans working and studying here. People
move around. That actually is quite good all round. It gives people a
wide experience and actually helps to generate scientific research as
well as employment opportunities across the whole continent. Is there
an upper limit? I don't think you can have one while
you have the free movement of Labour. The free movement of Labour
means you have to balance the economy, so you have to improve
living standards and conditions. That means the European Union's
appalling treatment of Greece, particularly the European central
bank as well as the European Union, that is a problem. So if you
actually deliberately lower living standards and increase poverty in
certain countries in south-east or Eastern Europe, then you're bound to
have a flow of people looking for somewhere else to go. Surely the
issue is, an and your sturdy, an growth package right across Europe.
So you can call yourself unequivocally a pro-immigration
politician? Brendan Cox, whose wife was killed, has said that
politicians at the top have been far too feeble in making the case for
immigration. They have allowed the argument to be made by the far
right. I spoke to Brendan last night and we were talking about this whole
issue, that the far right have been allowed to grasp the agenda. Nigel
Farage for example puts up that appalling poster, which has a
picture of a lot of desperate he pulled fleeing from war, saying,
they are coming to threaten us. Hello jigger I think Williams called
it right this morning when he said, we have to play our part in dealing
with the refugee crisis, all of us. It is a humanitarian crisis. But
there are lots and lots and lots of people around this country who do
feel that immigration is a problem for them. They feel their community
is changing very quickly, they feel their identity is challenged. They
are not racists, not far right people, just people really worried
about immigration. They feel that people like you are not listening to
them. I am not calling them racists. What I am saying is, it is a failure
of our government not to fund local authorities, not to provide housing
for people, and for the first time in 25 in 30 years, attacking school
budgets. It is that which is the problem, and they should turn their
anger against this government and the austerity which has been put
forward by Cameron and Osborne over the past six years. Your deputy, Tom
Watson, has said there has to be an end put to the free movement of
people, there has to be limits on migration - do you agree with him?
Tom and I had a chat about this. All of us are agreed that there has to
be a greater equality of working conditions. There has to be the
prevention of undercutting. There has to be an end to the idea of a
race to the bottom in working conditions. At the end of the day,
workers working alongside each other should be treated the same and have
the same rights. They should be paid the same. They don't, at the moment.
There are people watching right now who say, here is someone who is in
favour of uncontrolled immigration - that terrifies me. Those people now
have no choice but to vote to leave the EU. There is no uncontrolled
immigration. There is free movement of people across the EU, which goes
both ways. More than 2 million British people are living in Europe.
It goes both ways. There's uncontrolled immigration from
outside Europe, and there has been certainly ever since the 1960s in
quite a severe form. I represent a very mixed constituency, where there
are great problems of getting family reunion, and there are not equal
rights for people coming from Europe. They do not get benefits
immediately, they do not get access to housing immediately. It is not
totally uncontrolled. But in terms of EU migration, there is no way of
a British Government controlling that, and therefore, people worried
about that should vote for Brexit, because that is the only answer? It
is the very principle of a single market across Europe, the free
movement of people. If you have the free movement of capital, you should
also have the free movement of people. What I should think is we
should turn our issues on austerity in this country and indeed the
generality of austerity across Europe. We should also turn our
attention on tax havens and tax avoidance, which has only latterly
begun to be dealt with by the European Union. Britain has a big
role in this because as ground dependent territories, we have quite
a lot of tax havens. People might come to your constituency and say,
Mr Corbyn, I am really worried about the sheer number of people coming
here. I am sorry you do not agree, but it worries me a lot. Those
people are now moving towards the Leave side of the argument. If we
leave as a country, it will be partly because lots and lots of
Labour voters outside the metropolis and outside Scotland and the rest of
England, vote Leave. If we leave as a country, exactly the same
arguments will be made - about housing, about jobs, about social
security. All of those issues will be exactly the same on Friday as
they are on Thursday. The only thing is, it's going to be very much more
difficult, because the trade arrangements with Europe are now
quite deeply embedded to keep very large number of jobs in Britain do
depend on exports to Europe. I do not believe in catastrophe
arguments, but I say people should think very, very carefully about the
direction in which we are going. If we want to have good conditions and
good social security for all of us, that means it has to be thought of
in this country, but also across Europe as a whole. And also, let's
not turn our back on the humanitarian crises which exist
around the world. I ask people to think very carefully on the very
wise words of Rowan Williams this morning. Thank you for talking to us
today. In a moment, I'll be
talking to Michael Gove. But first, with only four days to go
till voting in the EU referendum, details of a special
programme coming up. Join us from Wembley Arena,
where key figures will be debating the most
important issues And it will be in front
of a live audience of thousands in a final
attempt to persuade you of We've just heard from Jeremy Corbyn,
reflecting on the death of Jo Cox and what it means for the tone
of political debate in this country and for the security of MPs
as they go about their work. I'm joined now by the Justice
Secretary, Michael Gove. Welcome to you. As Justice
Secretary, and as a parliamentarian, what are your reflections on Jo Cox,
did you know her at all? I did not know her well but I was tortured
fortunate enough to meet her almost on her first week in the House of
Commons, when we were in the tearoom and had forgotten her cash so I lent
her a ?5 notes to get a cup of tea. Did you get it back? Absolutely. I
struck up a conversation with her at the time, and had a few subsequent
conversations, and as so many people who knew how far better than me have
said, she is an amazing and wonderful person. She was a very
vivid parliamentarian. Yet she spoke with great passion and
effectiveness, she campaigned for causes she believed in with a great
heart. And I think she was the sort of person who all of us would want
our daughters to grow up to be like. She was an amazing person. I can
only grieve for her and in particular think of her poor
children and her Brive is burned, and I know the thoughts and prayers
of many of us at this time are with them. What is your view on the
debate we have been talking about on this programme about security for
MPs? I know all of you want to be out there on the front line, but
there is an issue now. A lot of female MPs in particular have become
worried about physical threats, rape threats, made against them regularly
on social media. People listen to these threats, and sometimes,
tragically, they act on them. You're right. Female colleagues in
particular have been subjected to the most horrendous abuse on social
media outlets like Twitter. I am thinking of Lucy, the incredibly
impressive and brave Labour MP who has faced horrendous anti-Semitic
abuse. Stella Creasy, again, a great camp pain, and my colleague Nicky
Morgan, who has also been on the receiving end. I think we need to
take a step back and think what we can do in order to make sure that
people in the public eye are kept safe. But I say two other things. It
is really important that members of Parliament remain accessible, as
Nicholas Soames and Kate Hoey said earlier. We are public servants. We
are there to be in touch and to reflect what our voters want us to
argue for. And therefore I think we must not try to need seal MPs away
from people whom we serve and one other thing - there are other public
servants who run daily risks, and as Justice Secretary, I think of prison
officers, those who work in the court system and police officers as
well. While I have been Justice Secretary, there have been
horrendous assaults against prison officers, and of course there has
been the murder of a police officer as well on, where side. So don't
forget them. -- on Merseyside. There are so many dedicated public
servants whose hard work we need to honour and whose safety needs to be
in the forefront of our mind. Sir Nicholas Soames said that the tone
of the political debate in this country has become more and more
aggressive and perhaps excessive as well. In the course of this
referendum debate, we all want robust arguments, but it has become
a little bit over the top, has it not worry people on both sides have
been pointing the finger, accusing each other of being traitors and
lying and all the rest of it - has it been too aggressive? Of course,
there have been moments when individuals have said things which I
certainly would not endorse. But I am very strongly in favour of free
speech. I think one of the things which is central to a healthy
democracy is the belief that people can express themselves and expressed
deep feelings with passion and force. One of the things not just
about this referendum campaign, but election campaigns as well, is that
people need to hear the arguments laid out, and the Advocate should
begin an affair run. I certainly think that there have been people on
the Remain side and on the Leave side who have made powerful,
impressive and passionate arguments. When we think about what is precious
in our democracy, and it is our democracy which we will be voting to
decide on, on Thursday, when we think about what is precious, then
free speech, robust debate, that is at the heart of our democracy. And
you don't think it has gone too far? Sadiq Khan, who knows a thing or two
about robust debate, has been talking about a climate of hatred,
negativity and cynicism. First of all, I admire Sadiq Khan, I think he
is proving to be, in his first few weeks, a good Mayor of London. I
entirely understand, after having been through a male role campaign,
why he will reflect on politics in that way. But I take a slightly
different view. -- a mayoral campaign. Instead of commentating on
the campaign, it is the responsibility of people like myself
in any campaign to make arguments. I entirely respect the right of
commentators like yourself and others, to draw conclusions and to
mark our homework, as it were. But I don't think we politicians should
mark our own homework. It is important for us to outline what we
believe and then let the people make a judgment. I don't think I would
dare module homework, Michael Gove. I know it was not your poster, but
that famous poster which went out a couple of days ago, from the Ukip
side of the Leave campaign, which had a big crowd of migrants, most of
them brown skinned, and it just said, breaking point - what do you
think about that kind of rhetoric? When I saw that poster, I shuddered.
I thought it was the one thing to do. Again, I must stress, I believe
in free speech. I don't want to deny anyone a platform. When I have had
the opportunity to talk about migration during the course of this
debate, I hope I have been very clear. I am pro-migration, but I
believe that the way in which we secure public support for the
continued benefits which migration brings, and the way we secure public
support for helping refugees in need, is if people feel that they
can control the overall numbers coming here. In Canada and
Australia, they have control, and therefore they are able both to
welcome economic migrants and refugees. I understand that. Let me
look to you what the statement said on Turkey. Since the birth rate in
Turkey is so high, we can expect to see an additional million people
from Turkey alone in the EU within eight years. Crime is far higher,
and so far... It sounds a bit like, those people are the threats. Are
you happy with the tone of that? Yes, because I think it is important
to stress that when we are thinking about the enlargement of the
European Union, it is the official European Union policy to accelerate
Turkey's accession to the EU. And a number of politicians, including
Theresa May, have said that at the moment they do not think that is
right. In particular, I have pointed out that the Turkish president has
been taking his country in a direction which I do not think is
progressive. All absolutely true. But within eight years? The Prime
Minister says Turkey would not be a member of the EU until the year
3000. The fact that the British government
wants Turkey to join is clear. The rate and speed will depend on a
bright era of political factors but it is the case that during the
course of this year the European Union has said it wants to
accelerate that process. When Turkey is becoming less democratic, that is
not the right thing to do. Does the talk of birth rates make you a
little queasy? It is important to take into account numbers overall.
The important thing is we benefit from migration. If the numbers are
controlled. We know that when Romania and Bulgaria joined the
European Union, there were predictions on either side about the
numbers that would come. Those people at the higher end of the
estimates were correct. It puts a strain on public services and it is
important when we're thinking about migration to look at numbers and to
make sure there is a balanced approach. Michael Heseltine said,
the Brexit case depends on fanning fears about immigration. I am amazed
that someone like you marches to the drum of my Farage, Donald Trump and
Le Pen. I think our campaign, which I must stress is cross-party, and
has the support of people like Frank Field and Kate Hoey from the Labour
Party people like David Owen, an Independent Democrat. It has been
characterised by the breakfast of voices. It is not the people who
have been leading the league campaign. It has been people like
Kate, Frank, David Owen and myself and Boris Johnson, who are not cut
from the cloth that Michael refers to. Let's move on to the economic
side of the argument. What will happen is inevitably some kind of a
gamble. Even if you say that the Treasury warnings are far too
extreme and some of the stuff we have heard about economic Armageddon
are going way, way over the top. Going from where we are now to a new
place does involve a job. We have talked about bumps in the road.
Michael Howard has said he does not worry about that. Surely you have to
accept it is a gamble we will be taking if people vote to leave. I
would not use the word gamble but I want to be absolutely clear about
this. Whichever way we vote, there are risks to our future and
challenges in the global economy. My view is the risks will be less and
the challenges will be easier to need if we vote to leave because we
will have control of the economic levers, the money we centred
European Union, the control over our laws. As a result will be able to
deal with whatever the world throws at us because people making
decisions on our behalf are emotionally invested in our future,
not people in Brussels and Strasbourg who are making decisions
based on factors. Millions of people are looking for unimpeachable
authority. If you work for Hitachi, who have said they will look again
at investment in this country or Rolls-Royce same thing, or John
Lewis, or JP Morgan, who are threatening jobs. They will listened
to their own bosses and rightly so full that they know about their own
industries. What is striking is there are so many bosses and
corporate leaders who have said, whatever happens they will continue
to invest in this country because the educational achievements, the
generosity of spirit, the hard work and creative genius of the British
people makes them believe in this country. More than that, there have
been a number of very important business people, James Dyson and
Bamford, for example. He and Anthony Bamford and Simon Wells, all of them
are very clear we would be better off if we left the European Union.
If you would not use the word gamble about taking the choice to leave, it
is a big, big change. What word would you leave? What it would be
would be an affirmation of faith and hope in Britain. I think Britain
will be taking its place alongside countries like Australia, Canada,
New Zealand and America as a self-governing democracy. Democracy
is one of the great gifts we gave the world. Other countries which
emulated our approach have prospered and that is a wonderful thing. I
think if we voted to leave, what we would be doing is saying the British
people, in their wisdom and generosity, have the ability to not
just govern themselves well but to be a progressive beacon to the
world. You mentioned Australia. The points system on immigration looks
like a very detailed manifesto to be handed to whoever is Prime Minister
after the result from the referendum. Is that on the ballot
paper? You have made various promises and listed bills with
European law, the Special Finance Bill, it looks like a manifesto. It
is a clear outline of the things we could achieve and we voted to leave.
Everything we have talked about, our policies we could embark on, they
are changes we could make which would benefit this country. If we
voted to leave, one thing is BLT on domestic fuel. We cannot remove VAT.
-- VAT. It would be a good thing and help the very poorest in society. Is
this on the ballot paper? People voting to leave the EU should know
this can only happen if we vote to leave. Do go to David Cameron
saying, here are the things you must do? I would say, now we have left
the European Union and there has been a clear vote, an instruction
from the electorate to us as a team to implement it, now is the time for
us to implement these proposals and give people both the tax reduction
that they hoped and believed we could receive only outside the
European Union and also the boost to the National Health Service. He
believes that leaving the single market will put a bomb under the
economy and does not believe in the Australian points system and so
forth. If he stayed on as Prime Minister, would he not simply be a
hostage Prime Minister, a puppet Prime Minister, doing what he is
told by the Brexiteers and the Tory Party? A humiliation for him.
Absolutely not. One thing about the Prime Minister if he is a Democrat
Patriot. When we had a vote in the House of Commons of intervention in
Syria in the last parliament, the vote went against the Prime Minister
and in what I believed. As a Democrat and patriot, he respected
that vote and then sought to follow the instructions the House of
Commons had given. On this occasion, the Prime Minister, if we vote to
leave, I know he will respect that instruction. We were elected on a
manifesto of which the referendum was part. There are also reforms of
the education system and the National Health Service which is at
the heart of what David Cameron wants to guarantee. I am 100% behind
all of that. What about the comparison budget that George
Osborne came up with? How can he have authority as Chancellor? I did
not say I thought the situation would arise. George has been an
outstanding Chancellor and he has rescued our economy from the
difficult circumstances we inherited in 2010. During the course of the
campaign, different sides, the Remains side, will make political
interventions. I disagree with that political intervention. It does not
in any way remove my admiration and respect for him. You could not sit
inside a cabinet and vote down what the Chancellor has said. -- Cabinet.
The argument that was made, on the basis of a speculative report, the
country might lose a significant amount of money if we were to leave,
I think that speculative report was wrong, our economy would be stronger
if we voted to leave the European Union and the situation does not
arise. A leading Tory donor said, business has lost trust in the
Chancellor because of the big manipulation of figures in the
referendum and a very strange arguments were so aggressive and
without proper evidence about what would happen will be to leave the
EU. For political union of the party, we need to think about the
new Chancellor. I completely disagree with that. I am a
free-speech guy. I respect the right people to put their cards on the
table. I think our economy is stronger with George Osborne as
Chancellor and I think our economy would be stronger if we voted to
leave. We would be able to spend hundreds of millions of pounds on
our priorities, like the NHS. Final quote from John Major. On the NHS,
it is like a small hamster. You are a hungry pipe and a new cannot be
trusted with the NHS. -- Tyson. I have enormous respect for the
National Health Service and for him. But first, a look at what's coming
up after this programme. We talk about the legacy of Jo Cox.
The reaction to the Church of England is praying for health. As
Tim Peake returns to Earth, we are asking, should we spend more on
space? Join us at 10am, if you can. We're nearly out of
time for this morning. On The Sunday Politics in an hour,
Andrew Neil will be talking to the former Liberal Democrat
leader Lord Ashdown. I'll also be talking
to the actress Helen McCrory, and no doubt some
political guests, too. But we leave you now with the young
singer and songwriter Jake Bugg. From his brand new album,
On My One, this is Love, # Crying for the one
who doesn't love you # You don't know why
he doesn't want you # So dry those eyes
and don't be afraid # Crying for the one
who doesn't love you # You don't know why
he doesn't want you # So dry those eyes
and don't be afraid # Cause the rhythm of
lovers ain't the same # No, you don't know it don't
come easy, come easy # I'm the first to have gone
and tell me if I'm wrong # I hope that I am
and you don't hate me # And I know, and I know
that you must hate me # Holding back the reasons
not to love you # But when you're
feeling down and lonely # So dry those eyes
and don't be afraid # Cause the rhythm of
lovers ain't the same # No, you don't know
it don't come easy # I'm the first to have gone
and tell me if I'm wrong # I hope that I am
and you don't hate me # And I know, and I
know, and I know that