Good evening. APPLAUSE
Good evening and welcome to Wembley and the great debate, voting now
only one day away in the most important decision the United
Kingdom has been asked to make in a generation. And here in the SSE
Arena several thousand voters divided equally between supporters
of Leave and Remain have come together to listen to the final
appeals of each side. All the main speakers here on stage were
nominated by the designated campaigns. Speaking in favour of
leaving are the former Mayor of London, Boris Johnson, the Labour
MP... APPLAUSE
The Labour MP Gisela Stuart and the Conservative Energy Minister an
threea Ledson. APPLAUSE
Speaking in favourite of remaining in the European Union, the leader of
the Conservative Party in Scotland, Ruth Davidson. The Mayor of London,
Sadiq Khan. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
And Francis O'Grady, General Secretary of the TUC. Also with us
here in the arena, at the other end of the arena is Mishal Husain with
other guests, who are going to be listening to what's being said up
here and commenting on. It Yes, I'll get reaction from my panel of
guests, representing Leave and Remain, business people, politicians
and others, who've played a part in the referendum campaign. I'm in the
media spin room, where we'll be getting instant reaction to the
debate from political campaigners and from the press and fact checking
with the BBC's reality check team. And if you want to take part from
home in the debate on social media, you can use the hashtag BBC debate,
go to BBC News, on Facebook, where you can post your questions and
comments. There's also an instant fact checking on our website,
bbc.co.uk/realitycheck. Now a few moments ago the two sides drew lots
to decide who would start the debate. The Leave side won and
they've chosen Gisela Stuart, briefly, to summarise their
argument. APPLAUSE
Ask yourself just one question, if we were not in the EU today would we
join it? And if the answer is no, then on Thursday you will vote Leave
and take control. The European Union was a noble dream in the last
century, but today, it has failed. It has turned into a nightmare. I'm
a mother and I'm a grandmother and I think it is terrible that 50% of
young people in Greece don't have a job. The only continent with a
growth rate lower than Europe is Antarctica. By being in the EU, we
lose control of billions of pounds every year. It doesn't have to be
like this. We can take back control over our laws. We can take back
control over our taxes. We can take back control over our borders,
immigration policy and security. You know, sometimes voting doesn't make
much difference. On Thursday, it really does. You will decide who
makes decisions about the future of this country, so, take back control
and vote Leave. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Thank you. Now to open the debate for the Remain side, their choice,
Sadiq Khan. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Good evening. In just two days' time, we will make the most
important decision for a generation. Tonight, Ruth, Francis and I will
set out the positive and patriotic choice to remain in Europe. You and
your family will be both better off and safer. Your job will be more
secure and your wages will be higher. The prices you pay in the
shops will be lower and your rights at work will be protected. As a
lawyer, I learned to listen to the experts and follow the evidence.
Well, the evidence is undeniable and all the experts agree - we are
stronger, safer and better off in Europe, even those who want us to
leave admit that it's a big gamble. If there's one thing you should
remember when you go to vote, it's this: If we as a country decide to
quit, then we're out for good. There's no going back. Being
outwards and looking and forming alliances makes our country so
great. I urge you to make the positive and patriotic choice and
vote Remain. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Thank you. Now the questions that we've picked for debate tonight come
from our huge audience, obviously they can't all ask a question. But
we've divided the questions up into three sections - the economy,
immigration and Britain's place in the world. The key issues, those
three key issues are what we're doing. First, before we go to the
questions, we want to give you an objective view of the issues that
are at stake. Let's have a look at the issues that both sides have
identified on the economy. The UK economy is the fifth largest
in the world and the second largest in the European Union, after
Germany. Exports to countries in the EU account for 44% of everything we
sell abroad. Last year, we exported goods and services worth ?223
billion to the EU, and ?288 billion to the rest of the world. Imports
from the EU amounted to ?291 billion, which means we have a trade
deficit of ?68 billion a year with the EU. All this trade takes place
within the EU's single market. That means there are no tariffs on goods
moving between EU countries. Leave campaigners say that would also be
possible under future trade deals, if we vote to leave. The single
market means a common set of rules and standards for almost all goods
and many services, rules that are enforced by the European Court of
Justice. Remain supporters say that makes it harder for other countries
to discriminate against British companies and that being in the
single market is good for jobs. Leave supporters say it means all
British firms are bound by EU regulations which add unnecessary
red tape and are often imposed without UK support. So when it comes
to the economy, which is the best path for Britain - to Remain or to
Leave? So let's go to our first question,
which is from a Leave supporter. I run a small business, employing
ten local staff, and have been stifled by the raft of EU
legislation that's been imposed on me. What benefits are there for
small business owners of remaining in the EU, as I can't see any? Ruth
Davidson. Thank you, Maxine. Small businesses are the backbone of our
economy. I know that some people can find the EU a bit frustrating and
fussy, but what it does, it provides a level playing field, so that you
can't be undercut by other companies in other parts of the world. That's
why eight out of ten of the CBI's small business members want to stay
in the EU. We also help to write those rules. If we came out of the
EU, we wouldn't have a seat at the table. If we wanted to trade in the
EU, the other countries could put on tariffs and taxes, so you couldn't
sell to all of these other nations, the biggest free trading block in
the world, for free. It would cost us more money. That would hurt our
economy. It would also hurt jobs in this country. I want our economy to
grow and not shrink. The other side haven't told us what would replace
the single market. They haven't told us how many jobs would be lost. They
haven't told us how long new trade deals will take. They haven't told
us how big the hit will be. I don't think that's good enough when you go
to vote. You have to know or don't go, vote to remain to the biggest
trade deal that we can get in the world. All right.
APPLAUSE I'm going to try to give equal time
to both sides tonight. Boris. Thank you very much. I must say that I
think it was extraordinary to hear that we would have tariffs imposed
on us, because everybody knows that this country receives about a fifth
of Germany's entire car manufacturing output, 820,000
vehicles a year. Do you seriously suppose that they are going to be so
insane, as to allow tariffs to be imposed between Britain and Germany?
CHEERING I've been listening to businesses large and small, up and
down our country, over the last few months. I've been amazed how many
passionately want to come out of the single market, because of the rules
and regulation that's it imposes. 100% of UK businesses, even though
only 6% only do any trade with the rest of the EU. I'm listening to
some of the most extraordinary success stories of UK manufacturing
- JCB, the makers of the fantastic diggers that are building this city,
building roads and cities around the world. They want to come out of the
EU and not just JCD, but James Dyson, the single biggest
manufacturer of vacuum cleaners in Germany! All right, Boris. He wants
to come out. Just let me finish this point. He's telling the papers
tonight that he thinks staying in would be an act of economic
self-harm. All right. The way to more wealth and more jobs is to
leave, vote leave. Take control on Thursday. Sadiq Khan. I'm pleased
you're speaking to people, Boris, and I hope you're listening to. One
of the people you're listening to is a chap called Patrick Minford, he's
your chief economic advisor. Now Patrick said and I quote, "Leaving
will eliminate manufacturing. Over time, if we left the EU, it seems
likely we would most likely eliminate manufacturing, but this
shouldn't scare us." Let me tell you, to those 2. 5 million who work
in manufacturing, it scares them. It scares their family and it scares
me. Thank you. Well I ran financial services businesses for 25 years. I
did a tint as City minister and I'm a mum. I genuinely believe our
future will be so much brighter if we vote Leave and take back control
of our trade. The European Union has been a disaster for UK trade with
the rest of the world. It is true to say if we remain in, we're already
one of the biggest contributors to the EU, their failed euro project is
going to cost us so dearly. We will be paying for it forever. Not only
that, the EU wants to expand its borders to include Turkey and we
simply cannot afford it. We need to take back control and vote Leave on
Thursday. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Francis, just a reminder, Maxine's question was what benefits there are
for small business owners. I was going to say that Maxine, your
question is about small businesses and there are lots of small
businesses in Britain that have a pretty tough time, but many of them
are also parts of supply chains. The Leave side roll out JCB, but that's
one company. All the experts are saying that the economy would take a
big hit if we came out of the EU, that we trade -- trade would be more
hit as well. If you don't believe the experts, then listen to the shop
floor, because I'm here representing workers tonight. Union reps from
BMW, Toyota, Ford, Nissan, you name is, across the manufacturing sector,
they are saying we cannot afford this gamble with our jobs, our
wages, our livelihoods and our rights.
Gisela. Maxine, as someone who run as small business you know you don't
have time to lobby in Brussels. That's why the big companies like
Brussels, because they are all just lobbying to have their rules
imposed. APPLAUSE. And you are left with
having to comply with them. What I find is where the real job
generators are the small businesses like yours. Let's say what will
happen after we vote to leave. The income payments, the chair of the In
campaign, Sir Stuart Rose of M, said it is not going to be a step
change or somebody is going to turn the lights out. And then very
importantly, he said wages will go up. That should be something that is
really very important, because the pressure at the same time of
uncontrolled immigration, which is what the Bank of England has said,
that with every 10% you've got a suppression of 2% on wages. So for
small businesses you are better off, take back control and leave.
APPLAUSE. Do you want to come back on that? I do. Let's be honest,
workers in this country have already been through a rough time. That was
nothing to do with this debate. That was to do with all those bankers who
crashed our economy. And workers ended up paying the price. So when
we talk about wages, the TUC has looked at all the hard evidence.
What it shows, what we can see is that in the long run, because our
economy would be hit, good jobs like the ones in BMW and the car
factories would be replaced by worse ones like Sports Direct and zero
hours, and Wetherspoons for that matter. Alright. Wages would drop in
the long run by ?38 a week. That's filling up your petrol tank in a
small car. That's a big hit and we can't afford it. Don't take the
risk. Andrea? Thank you. Frances, what Len McCluskey, the boss of
Unite union, the biggest union, has said is that in the last ten years,
the EU's accession plans have created gigantic experiment at the
expense of ordinary workers. The result has been sustained pressure
on living standards, a systemic attempt to hold down wages and to
cut costs of social provision for working people. The EU has also
created 50% youth unemployment right across southern Europe. It's a total
(Inaudible) for a generation of young people. Andrea, we are talking
about British jobs and we have the highest level of employment in our
country's history. If you want to trade quotes, let's talk about what
your side have been saying. Boris Johnson, his Chief Economist says it
will eliminate manufacturing. He also said the EU would generate an
economic shock. Michael Gove says it will mean inevitably bumps in the
road. He said he can't guarantee that people won't lose their jobs. I
cannot question that every person currently in work in their current
job will keep their job. Boris Johnson said, will there be job
losses, there might or there might not. That is not good enough. That
is not good enough. CHEERING. It hasn't taken them long.
Boris? It hasn't taken them long... Hold on. They told us they would
have a positive and patriotic case and they are back to Project Fear
within moments. CHEERING. I want to protect British
workers. It is positive. They have nothing positive to say. I want
to... Hold on. Lord rose... Everybody will have their chance,
but if you speak one at a time, everybody here can hear and
everybody at home can hear. Boris. Thank you. It was Lord Rose who said
clearly that there would be no shock, that things would go on as
they are. Except for one thing. He said people on low incomes, as
Gisela rightly said, would get a pay rise. He was supported in that view
by somebody on the panel opposite. It is no less a figure, I will leave
you to guess. Somebody said that in too many places immigration has
driven down local wages. Now, who do you think that was on the panel
opposite? It was Sadiq Khan. I think he was making a good point.
APPLAUSE. No I didn't, Boris. As a Conservative, and I'm a proud
Conservative and a believer in free markets, the differentials in
incomes in our country have become too great. It is wrong that FTSE 100
chiefs are earning 150 times the average pay of people on the shop
floor. It would be a fine thing if as Lord Rose said people on low
incomes got a pay rise as a result of us taking back control of our
country and our system. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE. Boris, can I
ask you a question? I don't think it is unreasonable that people are
worried about their local hospital, worried about their local school,
worried what would happen if our economy went into recession or if
they lost their jobs or business struggles. All the experts say, and
you know this, leaving the EU would cause problems from our country.
Most recently as today, the chap who predicted the crash in 2008, what
did he say, Boris? He said Brexit could stall the UK economy and tip
us into recession. It is not unreasonable for a mum and dad
worried about paying the bills to ask the question, what is your plan?
A slogan is not a detailed plan. We want an answer to the question, what
is your plan? How would you make sure the terms of trade with the EU
are better than they are now? How would you make sure jobs won't
suffer? How would you make sure small businesses won't suffer? The
last time there was a recession, hard-working people in this country
suffered, many lost their homes. What's important, Boris, you ask the
question, but what is your plan? APPLAUSE. The point is, we are as
things stand spending billions every year that go into a big black hole
in the European Union and it's going to get worse. All the Remain side
have to talk about is Project Fear. We are the fifth biggest economy in
the world. We will be able to have free trade once we are free of the
European Union that has done a terrible job negotiating free trade
for us. Even Switzerland and Singapore, far smaller economies,
have been able to negotiate more than five times the value of the
free trade of the European Union. APPLAUSE. Vote to leave on Thursday.
We have a second question. It is on the economy and it is from Miranda,
who is supporting Remain. As a black British woman, I am grateful for the
protections the EU has provided me in the workplace and in wider
society. If we leave the EU, will this be the beginning of a slippery
slope towards weaker employment and social rights in the UK?
APPLAUSE. Andrea? Thank you very much for your question. The truth is
that UK governments have led the way in providing good rights for
workers, even before the European Union came into existence we had
equal pay legislation. It's been... Governments of all parties have
created minimum wage legislation, now a National Living Wage, shared
parental lead, ad, child-free tax care -- tax-free childcare. It is
this country that is protecting workers' rights. We do not need an
unelected bureaucratic European leaders who none of us can even
name, let alone who any of us voted for, to tell us what our workers'
rights can be. We should take back control and look after our own
society. APPLAUSE. It is a question about
employment and social rights. Do you want to start? It is a really
important question from Miranda, because too often we hear the words
red tape and what they are really talking about is getting rid of
vital rights at work that we all rely on.
APPLAUSE. Now, these rights weren't gifted to us. We fought over
generations, over boted to us. We fought over generations, over
borders, trade unions - all of us fought author these rights. But the
EU guarantees them. These are really important to our real lives. People
don't always understand this. This about if your child is sick, getting
emergency leave to look after them. Them. It is about equal rights for
part timers and agency workers. We hear a lot about holidays, when the
working time directive came in, 2 million people in Britain got paid
holidays for the first time. Mainly women, mainly young people. Do you
trust them, can they promise us today, because I've heard a lot from
some of these leading lights in the Leave campaign and what they plan to
do on employment rights, can you promise us today that you will
protect each and every single right that we won through the EU? Alright,
that's the question. Gisela. We have done already. Already. I first
joined the trade union 45 years ago when I was an apprentice and I
though that strong trade unions, are best supported by Labour
Governments, protect rights. I find it extraordinary that I'm being told
that I can't trust you, the voter, to make sure we get a Government in
which protects workers' rights and we need Brussels to defend you.
APPLAUSE. The euro is a broken project. We are going to pay... No,
YOU are going to pay out of your taxes one bail-out after another.
And the European Union does not protect your jobs. Just a few years
ago, ford Transit got money from the European Union so they could take
their factory out of the United Kingdom and put it into Turkey. That
is wrong. APPLAUSE. Sadiq Khan. Miranda, I
would ask you a question, but Gisela, you are so wrong. Every time
we've been... Every time you and I have been in a lobby voting for
bills to give workers' rights, they've been in the other lobby
voting against those rights. APPLAUSE. Let me say this. Let me
tell you why you're wrong. Because Priti Patel let the mask slip. She
has said, if we could just halve the burdens of the EU social and
employment legislation, and let me tell you what that means. That means
rights for mums and dads. That means rights for part time workers who've
the same rights as full-time workers. Web the employer changes
ownership, they have rights. The worst thing for workers is their
bosses business going out of business. Them losing trade, losing
jobs. That's why we need a healthy economy. Gisela, you should know
better. APPLAUSE. Sadiq, the most important
worker's right is a right to a job. As long as we are shackled to a
failing eurozone liable to bail-out after bail-out, we will not succeed.
There's two points. Number one, the eurozone is growing faster than our
economy and the USA. Number two... You and I both fought an election
where these guys were boasting how brilliant our economy is, right?
They were boasting last year how brilliant our economy is. One of the
reasons why we are the fifth richest country is our role is enhanced by
being in the European Union. We are at the table helping the rules being
made. APPLAUSE. . Boris? In addition, it
beggars belief that the Remain side cannot think of a single one of the
EU's multitude of regulations they would get rid of, not even the
clinical trials directive, which prevents vital pharmaceutical work
being carried out. The EU I'm afraid is a job-destroying engine. You can
see it across Europe and you can see it, alas, in this country as well.
Gisela rightly mentioned the case of Ford. I would also mention what
happened to Tate Lyle, who tonight announced they want to come out of
the EU because of the destruction that the EU's Common Agricultural
Policy has wrought upon them. Not just on jobs in London but in the
developing world who want to export cane sugar to the EU. I would
also... APPLAUSE. I would mention Tata
Steel. We are told we cannot cut our energy costs to protect jobs in Port
Talbot because Brussels says no. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE. Nonsense.
It's a lie! Hold on. It is perfectly true. One lie after another after
another. Just cool it everybody for a moment. Ruth Davidson. You are
going to be asked to vote in two days' time and all you've heard is
trust us and it will all be fine. That's not good enough. They won't
tell us how much our economy will be hit by, won't tell us how many jobs
might go, what they are going to replace a single market with. If you
vote on Thursday, you cannot change your mind on Friday. If we vote to
come out of the biggest free trade bloc in the world, there'll be
tariffs put on British businesses. That will affect our ability to
trade abroad. It is not just the 27 we trade with now as part of the EU,
but there are 50 other countries in the world the EU has trade deals
with. If they come out, we go to the back of the queue. That's not
Project Fear. That's what Obama said. They want a deal with 500
million, not 50 million people. 80% of the world's economy is not in
the single market. The free trade deals that Ruth is talking about
that the EU has, those free trade deals are many of them, most of
them, 46 of the 50 countries are not in the single market. Many countries
in the world do more business with the EU than the UK does. You do not
need to be in the single market. We are the fifth biggest economy in the
world. Most economies can agree free trade deals within two years. The
European Union is taking ten years or never at all. Why? Because 28
member states cannot even organise a takeaway curry, let alone what
they're going to do on free trade with the rest of the world. All
right. The line was - we do not need to be in the single market. When you
are 5'6" it's not often you say size matters. But size matters awe the
bigger you are the -- because the bigger you are the more cloud you
have. -- cloud we have. Clout. If you are a company in China, America,
India, and you want to do business with 500 million customers, you can
have your headquarters in London and have a gateway to 500 million
customers. Boris you should know better. I speak to businesses around
our city every day of the week. You know what, half a million jobs in
London directly dependent on the European Union. I speak to companies
around the world, more than 60% of the world's leading companies, Sony,
AIG insurance, have their European headquarters, guess where? Here in
London. Half our exports goes to Europe. Boris, why have you suddenly
changed your mind? APPLAUSE
All right. Since we have a former Mayor of London and the present
Mayor of London... I think we've heard an amazing amount of running
down of our city and our country. We're proud of our city. The
astonishing thing is that they underestimate our ability to do
better deals if we're left to do it on our own. Let me give you an
example. Because of the EU system, our entire trade negotiating policy
is handed over to the EU Commission, where only 3. 6% of the officials
actually come from our country. It is no wonder that they have not
been, as Andrea rightly says, they have not done free trade deals with
China, India, the great economies of the world, including America, to the
extent, to the point where we - Just one question. We cannot because the
EU is in charge of our trade negotiations export Haggas. We
cannot export Haggas to America! Come on. Come on. All right. Boris.
Boris. Let's leave the haggis. Can you name me one country in the world
that has said it will give us a better deal if we come out of the
EU? The United States. Obama says we would go to the back of the queue.
All right. On that note, we have to move on. We've got a lot more to
talk about. We take a pause here where we can cool down. They'll warm
up again in a moment. Over to the other end of the hall here to hear
reaction from her guests to the debate so far.
David, throughout the course of the programme, we're going to be hearing
from this panel as well on the key issues. There are ten of them in
all, five from the Remain side and five from the Leave side. Let's
start our economic discussion over here with Priti Patel, Conservative
MP and Employment Minister. Are you part of a Government that asked
people to vote Ono the basis of not taking aI risk with the economy. How
does that square with what you're asking people to do now? We've heard
clearly tonight that we're the optimists. We have a brighter,
prosperous future outside the European Union, a complete contrast
to the Remain side that want to constantly talk Britain down. We've
heard clearly about the freedom to succeed, we can negotiate new trade
deals. It's pessimistic to hear from the Remain side that they're not
even interested in doing that. They don't want new partnerships. They
don't want new relationships. They clearly don't want to trade with the
2. 2 billion potential customers that exist globally in the
Commonwealth countries. That's about the future of our economy. Before I
go to the Remain side, I want to turn to you Tim Martin, founder and
chairman of Wetherspoons. Answer the charge that leaving the EU would
roll back workers' rights at a company like yours. It's complete
and utter nonsense. She picked on us for some reason. We pay 40% of our
profits as bonuses to staff that work in our pubs. No-one gets a
fortune, but I should have a reply to that, no-one gets a fortune, but
apart from John Lewis partnerships, so far as I'm aware, no-one pays a
bigger bonus to our staff. The rights that workers have now... We
will certainly not give up our workers' rights. Why do that? We
paid above what we had to for many years, long before the EU told us
what to do. Let me get a different perspective from business. This time
from Justin King, who ran one of our biggest supermarkets, Sainsbury's,
for ten years. Where Remain? This is presented as if it's a straight
choice. I think we can have the best of both worlds. We have a place in
Europe, which is unique and has allowed our country to prosper.
Almost everything the Remain camp is saying we ought to do, we can do
whilst still part of Europe. Germany's, four of their biggest
trading partners are outside of Europe. We are going to see real
damage to our economy. That's bad for small business, they'll be the
first to lose jobs. We'll see prices go up because our currency is going
to be hurt and a poorer economy means all the services, the taxes
and vibrant economy pay more will be harmed. You're sitting next to Sarah
Woollaston, until a short time ago you I Would Do Anything For Love
have been on the other side. I've listened to the evidence. It's clear
our NHS, health research will be hit if we leave. There will be less
money for those services and it will hit the workforce. It will hit our
leadership role in research and development and cooperation with our
European partners. There will be a very serious Brexit penalty for the
NHS, make no mistake. If people are caring about the NHS and research
when they make their vote, I would say vote to Remain with our European
partners. I will get a couple of quick thoughts. I want to turn to
you, from women for Britain. Work for Morrisons. What do you think
about what Justin King said about prices going up. I want to focus on
the rights, particularly what the Remain side were saying. We had the
first Equal Pay Act by the first female minister of state three years
before we joined the European Union. We have the sex discrimination act,
the domestic violent act -- violence act, and Margaret Thatcher the first
female Prime Minister without European Union assistance. Are you
seriously saying those rights and protections are just going to
disappear overnight? Of course not. A final thought now from Tim Farron.
You could dismiss the economic arguments as project fear. Nine out
of ten experts say we're better off in the European Union. Michael Gove
said we've had enough of experts, that's perhaps an explanation of why
he was such a dreadful Education Secretary.
CHEERING When I send my kids to school, I
want them to be taught by experts not the bloke down the pub. I went
to a small business in my constituency, they are exporting to
Romania. They provide play equipment over there. That contract is
entirely contingent, if we vote out on Friday, they lose that contract.
That's the case for hundreds of businesses across the country. Thank
you very much. More from this panel later on. David, back to you.
Now, the second topic is immigration. The second big argument
in this whole case. Before the questions and the debate, a reminder
of the question issues identified ash the subject -- around the
subject of immigration. 508 million people live in the
European Union. Freedom of movement means that all EU citizens have the
right to live and work in any member state. Last year net migration from
other EU countries, the difference between the number of people coming
into the UK and going out, was 184,000. From elsewhere in the wore,
it was 188,000. The European figure has risen a lot since the EU
expanded in 2004. There are now around three million citizens of
other EU countries living in the UK. An estimated 1. 2 million British
citizens living elsewhere in the EU. Because the UK is not a member of
the border-free Schengen area, anyone arriving here has to show a
passport and they can be refused entry if they're judged to represent
a serious threat to society. Last year, this happened to about 2,000
people from the EU. What about the future? Five countries have been
accepted as candidates for EU membership, Albania, Montenegro,
Macedonia, Serbia and Turkey. Current EU states have a veto over
any new members. Leave campaigners say staying in the EU means we won't
be able to control our borders or the level of immigration. Remain
supporters say EU immigration is good for the economy and planned
curbs on in-work benefits will reduce the incentive to move here.
So what has been the effect on Britain of EU migration? And is
immigration best managed within the EU or outside? So there's the issue,
our first question is from Jayne Williams, who is a Remain supporter.
My family and I have had first hand experience recently with the NHS.
How would it manage if we leave the EU, given the UK's inability to
train and retain sufficient doctors and nurses? Boris Johnson. I think
the first thing we should do tonight in a discussion about immigration is
celebrate immigrants and immigration and everything they do for our
country. Because I speak entirely personally, they are, my family has
benefitted massively from immigration and so, I know, have
millions of people watching us tonight. The crucial thing, though,
is to look in an informed way at what is going on, look at the
numbers, look at the pressure that is large-scale uncontrolled
immigration is causing for public services, such as the NHS. And the
downwards pressure on wages that I've already mentioned and that
Sadiq Khan has discussed. Look at the way in which we are forced by
our imbalanced system to push away people who might contribute mightily
to our NHS in favour of uncontrolled access to 510 million people from
the rest of the EU. What we think should happen is an
Australian-style, points-based system, so we get the people we need
for the NHS and indeed all our other businesses and services and the only
way you can do that is to vote Leave and take back control on Thursday.
Sadiq Khan. Firstly, Australia has double our
immigration, bearing in mind their population. I don't want facts to
get in the way Boris, of course, we need to have a fair immigration
policy. It shouldn't be a free for all. You don't hear me say this
often, David Cameron deserves credit for the deal he negotiated with the
EU. What it means is you pay in before you can take out. You have to
work four years before you can receive full benefits. Here's the
nub of it, immigration has brought huge economic, cultural and social
benefits to our country. The EU migrants more than 130,000 work in
the NHS and social care, thank you EU migrants work in our schools and
our construction sector. Thank you. More than 1. 5 million Brits
recommend ployed by companies owned by EU citizens here. Thank you. Are
employed. You might start off saying how wonderful immigration is. Your
campaign hasn't been project fear. It's been project hate as far as
immigration's concerned. CHEERING Gisela.
All right. All right. I am an immigrant. Sorry. I am an immigrant.
I'm also a mother and a grandmother. I think it is important that as we
plan for our public services, like the NHS, like the schools, like
housing, that we actually can plan ahead properly. And if we have
uncontrolled immigration, with the best will of the world, we will have
situations, like in the West Midlands, where there are 50,000
primary school places missing. This is simply a statement of fact. If
you cannot plan. What I object to... APPLAUSE
I think this is really important. The current immigration policies
unfairly discriminates against non-EU citizens.
APPLAUSE. Frances O'Grady. Jane made a really, really important point in
her question about our NHS. Let's not forget the NHS was built by and
for working people, and we should all be really proud of it.
APPLAUSE. But we've got thousands of EU nationals and from all ousands of
EU nationals and from all over the world - nurses, midwives, doctors,
other health professionals, the whole health team, working to save
lives and keep us healthier. We should give them credit where it is
due and recognise there would be a staffing crisis if we lost that
staff. There would be longer waiting lists, fewer life-saving drugs.
Drugs. David, if I may, I've got a really important question that I
just learned about today. Because today we learned that Vote Leave
took a 600,000 pound donation from a former member of the BNP. Are you
going to pay it back? APPLAUSE. A brief answer from one of
you to that question. That is unworthy of this debate.
CHEERING. There are millions of people who've very real and genuine
concerns about the impact of free movement on this country and who've
donated to a campaign to Vote Leave and take back control. The problem
with free movement, for me as a mum it is not just about uncontrollable
numbers coming here and putting pressure on public services. It's
all about security, for all of our children, for all of us. Free
movement does not allow us to even ask people if they have a criminal
record. The European Court has overruled British judges in being
able to deport criminals. We know Ron Noble, the former head of
Interpol, has said that the Schengen-free area in Europe is like
hanging out a sign welcoming terrorists to Europe. It is creating
enormous problems. APPLAUSE. Before I go to the other
side, can I remind you of Jane's question? The second half was, how
would we manage if we left the EU given the UK's inability to retain
doctors and nurses? As Gisela said, at the moment uncontrollable
immigration from the EU means we discriminate against 92% of the
world. There are brilliant health professionals in South-East Asia, in
China, in South America who would love to come here, but we have to
put up the barriers to them because we are required to allow people to
come here from the EU, whether or not they are trained to support our
health services. Thank you. Ruth Davidson. Immigration is hard and it
is really tempting to believe that there's one single silver bullet
like leaving theic that can fix it all. Yes, take back control. But
there is. We need a proper, credible plan to manage migration. They don't
have a credible plan, where you used to be able to come and take out
without putting in. That's changing. They say they want a points system.
Migration Watch says it will mean more people coming from outside the
UK to live here rather than yeah. Boris wants an amnesty for illegal
immigrants. They have had a poster in this campaign but they don't have
a plan for managing migration. There isn't a silver bullet.
APPLAUSE.. Gisela? I want to respond to some of the I think unnecessary
invective we heard earlier on by pointing out that somebody on the
panel opposite said only a couple of years ago, in the past we were too
quick to dismiss concerns about immigration, even worse accuse
people of prejudice. Who do you think that was? It was Sadiq Khan,
again. I do agree with Sadiq, you need a grown up approach to this.
I'm passionately a believer in immigration but it's got to be
controlled. When you've got numbers running at 330,000 net globally,
184,000 net from the EU, 77,000 coming without even the offer of a
job last year, it's obviously time to take back control, and the answer
to your question is have the Australian-style points-based
system. Boris, all of us accept that there are legitimate concerns about
immigration that need to be addressed. You are not being honest
by admitting you haven't got a silver bullet. You are scaring
people to vote to leave the EU. You are telling lies. Turkey is not set
to join the EU. Boris, you are telling lies and you are scaring
people, because you've used taxpayers' money to put out an
election leaflet that says Turkey set to join. There's a map, there's
a map. This map shows in red, Turkey, but the only countries named
in this map are Syria and Iraq. That's scaremongering Boris and you
should be ashamed. CHEERING. Gisela?
I would quite like the real David Cameron to step forward and tell us
what the policy on Turkey is. Because on the one hand he tells us
it will be the year 3000, or is it now 30 years? On the other hand, we
are spending ?1.9 billion of your money to accelerate accession of
Turkey. We've got a special section in the embassy to deal with speeding
up accession. He has just three months ago signed a joint statement
with all the other Heads of Government of the European Union to
accelerate accession. They are negotiating visa access of 1 million
from Turkey. He refuse to do so say he'll use his veto. Which David
Cameron are we going to believe? APPLAUSE. Ruth Davidson? Let me
answer on Turkish accession and let me say this. It is not going to
happen. It's just simply not on the cards. Not my words, Boris Johnson
said that on LBC Radio two months ago. Those were the words of Boris
Johnson two months ago. What's changed in two months, Boris? What's
changed in two months? It is simply not on the cards. It's Government
policy. It's Government policy. As far as I know last time I looked,
the Government wants to accelerate Turkish membership. I think Gisela
posed the dilemma clearly. It is something they want to happen in the
year 3000 or something they wish to accelerate. I think it is perfectly
reasonable to ask people whether they would rather proceed on the
basis of Government promises on immigration, or whether they would
rather take back control and institute a points-based system that
the electorate could actually hold the Government to account? The
problem at the moment... CHEERING AND APPLAUSE. The problem
at the moment. Boris! I'm trying to make a balance between the two
sides. I was asked the question. Forgive me. I know, but when you
talk at length, I have to go... Sadiq? Let's deal with this big fat
lie once and for all. Turkey isn't about to join. Until three months
ago you knew that was the case, Boris Johnson. In 1987 Turkey first
applied to join. There are 35 conditions, chapters... Allow him to
have his say, Boris. Of the 35 chanters, only one has been met. At
this rate it will take to the year 3000 this will they reach the
criteria. Uribe using the ruse of Turkey to scare people to vote to
leave. Youened aboth though there is no chance of them joining soon.
APPLAUSE.. We are moving on. Can I just say one thing to you in the
audience, I did say at the beginning of the debate, applause fine. Please
don't shout out, because you drown out the debate here and people at
home can't hear it. If you could just restrain yourselves, applaud if
you want to, but don't try to conduct a second debate with the
speakers on the panel. We are going to our next question, from Karim, a
Leave supporter. As a young working class man, I feel at the back of the
queue for entry level jobs, housing and public services. How many people
each year can the UK reasonably cope with? Frances O'Grady, your turn to
start. APPLAUSE. Well, there is no doubt
that we need to manage migration better. You're right, Karim, there
should be more opportunities, there should be more jobs, and not just
more jobs, better jobs. But I have to say I get fed up, migrants always
getting the blame for something that politicians in Westminster ought to
be doing something about. APPLAUSE. Because it seems to me
that zero hours, I want to tackle zero hours and I suspect everybody
else in this hall does too. Westminster can do something about
that. When it comes to paying a decent wage, that's Westminster's
job. And we really should be investing in more new homes, in
better public services where we have pressures on communities, our
schools and hospitals. Instead of cuts, we need investment. But
finally I've got to say why I get fed up with migrants being blamed
is, where did all this start? The big pressure on our pay and jobs
wasn't to do with low-paid migrant workers. It was those greedy bankers
crashing the economy, and if we leave will crash it again. Let's try
within reason to stick to the points we've been asked to raise. Rim
railed the point - how many people each year can the UK reasonably cope
with. Gisela? And that's the heart of the matter, the point you've just
raised, because any Government with the best will of the world when it
has to plan its public services, whether it is schools, whether it is
the NHS, whether it is training how many nurses and doctors we need,
housing, to get on the housing ladder, all those things are
impossible with the best will of the world if you have got uncontrolled
numbers comes in. Ave got uncontrolled numbers comes in. --
coming in. An Australian-type points system allows you to adjust things.
Australia happens to want more immigration because it is a large
country, but you want to reduce it. The one thing I find extraordinary,
uncontrolled immigration has allowed big companies not to do the kind of
training of our workers they ought to be doing, because they are able
to recruit cheap from the rest of Europe.
APPLAUSE. Ruth, Karim's question was he feels, he preface was he feels at
the back of the queue for entry level jobs for housing and public
services is. How many can the UK cope with? We do need to bring down
migration and looking at the skills you want to bring here. You used too
be able to come from the EU and take out the day you arrive. Now you have
to wait four years before you can take out full benefits. If you don't
find a job within six months, you can be asked to leave. Gisela talks
about public services, schools and hospitals, I don't think you can
discount the contribution migrants make, 150,000 in schools in England
and Wales. But my big issue is this. You don't fund schools and hospitals
and you don't control immigration by crashing the economy. That's what
leaving theic would do. APPLAUSE. Andrea? That is just
simply not the case. If we vote Leave and take back control this
Thursday, we will have a ?10 billion a year independence dividend that we
will be able to spend on our priorities. Not true. The Bank of
England has been very clear in its report, that uncontrolled
immigration has had downward pressure on wages in this country.
They simply haven't had a pay rise for years. Not only that, but every
family in this country knows how difficult it is to get the primary
school place of your choice, to get a doctor's appointment, and yes to
afford rents or to get on to the housing ladder. These are the really
legitimate concerns and the way to get over that is by voting Leave and
takeing back control on Thursday. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE. I've got to
come back on this. Immigration is a concern to a lot of people but
leaving theic isn't the answer. Yes, it is.
CHEERING. But it's not. How is it having more control if you have less
money in your pocket as Martin Lewis the money expert says? How is it
more control if we have a recession as the Bank of England says. How is
it more control if we are not investing in the schools and
hospitals and GP practices, if Karim can't get a job because local
employers are suffering, or how is it control if it is double the
immigration, and the points system, more control if there are businesses
from China, India and America choosing Germany and France over
London. How is it more control if young people don't have the
opportunity that we have? CHEERING.
I think Boris, it's your turn. Let me say directly to Sadiq Khan, I
think there's a lot of agreement around this panel. And they should
come over and join our side. Everything I've heard tonight is
their admission that something is wrong with our immigration system.
There's only one way to fix it and that is to take back control and day
after day, in the last week, we've seen senior figures in the Labour
Party, Jeremy Corbyn this morning, he's the leader...
LAUGHTER Said there was no way of controlling
immigration as long as we're in the EU. Tom Watson, Harriet Harman,
they're all finally accepting that the deal that was done did
absolutely nothing to restore control of our immigration system to
this country. There is only one way to achieve that.
APPLAUSE There is only one way to achieve
that and that is to vote Leave and take back control and put in the
Australian-style, points-based system that makes sure that we get
the people that we need to help our business, our NHS, but do not - I
find it a bit rich to listen to you... Boris, I find it a little bit
rich to hear people saying they're worried about wages, when your
Government has imposed a pay cap on six million public servants year
after year after year after year. Can I also say, Karim's question was
about numbers. I think the Leave campaign is selling people a big
con. Because you're not promising to reduce numbers. You have never
promised to reduce numbers. Yes, we have. And you're pretending that you
are going to reduce numbers. It's a big con. Don't believe them. This is
a one way ticket. If we're out, we're out. We will pay with our jobs
and wage it's we go. The accusation is that you've never
promised on the Leave campaign to reduce numbers, is that true? What
an Australian-style, points-based system would allow you is to decide
what the numbers are. At the moment, you can't. But can I just make
another point, this debate today actually isn't about - Sorry, can
you answer her point. APPLAUSE
Has the Leave campaign promised to reduce numbers? We say you take back
controll and you can decide. What we have not done is what the Prime
Minister has done and actually prom ilsed he would reduce it to the tens
of thousands, even though he couldn't do it. You're not
promising, it's a con. This is not about the six of us here on the
podium and the debate, this is about my children's future, your
children's future, our grand children's future. I think unless we
take back control over something as important as that we won't be able
to provide the public services they deserve.
APPLAUSE I do just have to remind people at
home in case they're mistaking that there are mums and dads and nans and
granddads on this side of the argument. The immigration issue is a
complex one which needs a grown up argument. We're not having it
tonight. Britain deserve better than people who say they have a quick fix
but won't tell you what it means for Britain. We need a much bigger
conversation than this. That just is completely nonsense. This country
will do incredibly well if we take back control and vote Leave. What we
will be able to do is to manage the numbers of people who are coming to
this country so that we can be fair to those who come here and fair to
those who already live here. What we've had for a number of years now
is a situation where people's pay is down, where the skills training is
down, where there's pressure on all of our public services, including
school places, doctors places and the housing market. The only way we
will ever get that back under control is if we vote Leave on this
Thursday. All right. Thank you very much. We'll take a brief pause again
and go to the other side of the hall.
Immigration has been an important part of this debate for the Leave
side. So let me start our discussion of it with the Remain side. Caroline
Lucas, Green Party MP, how would you address the real concerns that
people have about the impact of migration on housing, on school
places, on health? It's exactly about the real concerns, the real
concerns is about pressure. But that's not caused by immigration.
That is caused by successive governments' failure to invest in
those services. We have heard that you are far more likely to find
someone from another EU country treating you in the NHS rather than
getting in ahead of you. Migration is going to be a large part of this.
We have the freedom to live and learn, study and work in 27 other
countries ourselves. What an amazing gift is that? When you consider that
people coming to our country are bringing with them not only benefits
to our society and our culture, but also to our economy. Let us
ring-fence the money they are paying into our tax system and use that to
build leisure centres and libraries in those places under pressure, so
everybody can benefit. There's a two-way street here. I want to get a
thought from the SNP. Your party's rare in British politics, it has
campaigned for more immigration. I don't care if it's unpopular. Let's
stick with the facts. Migrants contribute more than they take out
of the system. Let me just say this much. I have been so depressed at
the state of the debate around immigration and the worst of that we
saw last week, when Nigel Farage unveiled a poster that I'm going to
say it was xenophobic and frankly, bordering on racist. Dianne James
from Ukip here should hang her head in shame and apologise to the
British people for lowering this debate into the worst type of
debate. Migrants contribute. They contribute to our public services.
They contribute to our economy. They even contribute to our cuisine. And
thank God for it. Let me turn to Dianne James now. Hang your head in
shame. Nigel Farage has apologised. Let's put a reality check, please.
That photograph - Are awe shamed of the poster? That photograph went up
on social media the minute the MP was murdered. It was taken down.
That picture and pictures exactly the same appeared in the media well
before in the early part of this year, highlighting what is
completely wrong with the Schengen system, what is completely wrong
with the EU fundamental tenent of freedom ever movement of people. I
want to turn to Tony Parsons. Is immigration part of why you want to
leave the EU? It's definitely part of. It I personally have nothing
against migrants. I like them so much I married one. I think it's a
bit rich that the Remain side are so devoid of any arguments that they
have to smear us as racists and bigots because we're not. Because we
love our country. We love our country. And I have not heard one
argument about how if we're too timid, if we're too frightened, too
small to leave this rotting carbuncle of the European Union, how
do we accommodate a third of a million people? Are you up for
sharing a platform with Ukip that unveiled that poster? I think
there's been a broad range of opinion. You can laugh all the like,
but you're so desperate, because you have no answers about how we build a
city the size of Wolverhampton every year because you can't answer it.
Thank you. I want to turn back to the Remain side. I want to turn to
Justin King. Your business, the business you used to run,
Sainsbury's, could just employ more British workers if we said goodbye
to freedom of movement. And they do. Sainsbury's and many other
businesses. There are more people born in the UK in work in the UK
today than at any time in our history. That is a fact. There are
more people in employment in total in this country than at any time in
our history. That's part of our economic success. Over 80% of
migrants are in work net, as we've heard, time and again, contributing
to our economy. That's a powerful part of our economic success. Answer
the point there about how we can cope with the population increase,
you care about the NHS, you're a former GP. How can we cope? It's
shameful to blame migrants for queues in the NHS. The queues will
get longer if we leave the EU on this Thursday. Absolutely make no
mistake, because there'll be less money to fund the NHS. There will be
fewer workers able to move here freely to work. There's another
point I'd like to make. I have heard from NHS staff, who have told me
that they now feel unwelcome in this country. What a disgraceful
situation. I want to say thank you to all those people working in our
NHS, please stay. We want you to stay.
We'll hear from this panel once more, before the end of the
programme. We will indeed. Now we have so far
this evening talked about the referendum outcome, how it would
affect the economy and immigration. Our final half hour, we're going to
debate the big issues of democracy, security and Britain's place in the
world. Just before we do, a reminder of how our relationship with the EU
has developed over the years. The EU began in 1951 as the European
coal and steel community, which had six members. The idea was to create
an economic area to bring European nations closer to together in the
wake of World War II. In 1973, the UK joined what had, by then, become
the European economic community. And in 1975, the British people voted,
for the first time, on the UK's membership, deciding to remain part
of the EEC or Common Market. In 1993, the treaty on European Union
was signed in Maastricht. It was widely regarded as a step change for
the European project because it legally established the EU as a
political as well as an economic union. It also laid the foundations
for the introduction of the sing the currency, which Britain chose not to
adopt. In 2004, more countries joined the EU. It now has 28 members
and there is the prospect of new nations joining, if they meet the
criteria for entry. But current EU states have a veto over any new
members. Senior EU leaders are talking about the creation of a
European Army, and a new European intelligence agency. Leave
campaigners say the EU has embarked on a relentless journey to create a
European superstate. Remain supporters say Britain can opt out
of future integration. The choice at this referendum is to decide which
path is best for Britain - to Remain or to Leave.
So, our first question in this section is from Douglas Warren. He's
a Leave supporter. Thank you, David. 40 years ago, the
UK voted to join a Common Market. If we vote to remain on Thursday, how
can we be sure that in another 40 years, we won't find ourselves in a
United States of Europe? APPLAUSE
Britain is a sovereign, independent country, just like Germany, just
like France. We retain control over our defence, over the pound, over
interest rates, over what we do in our schools, hospitals, our public
transport. We chose to join the EU and we're having a referendum to
decide whether Remain or Leave. I tell you why I think it's important
to Remain. If we choose to Remain, it means we're a member of a single
market of 500 million customers. We can do free trade with one set of
rules that we help make. I tell you this, if you're living in France,
you aren't any less French because you're a member of the EU. If you're
in Germany, you're no less German because you're in the EU. We're no
less British because we're in the EU. I just don't accept that there's
a tradeoff between trade and democracy. I think democracy is
enormously important. APPLAUSE
And what we've got now is an institution that has utterly
outgrown its historic roots, which were noble, has now become so
cumbersome and the real big difference was the introduction of
the euro. That means you've got a failing currency, which is producing
50% youth unemployment in Greece. They have to sort out their
problems. And the best way for us is actually trade with the world, don't
be this inward looking block and above all...
APPLAUSE Above all, you take back control
over all the decisions you have made, because in one in 28 and
another five countries joining, we will become increasingly
insignificant in making the decisions. So let's take back
control. APPLAUSE. Ruth, I will repeat
Douglas's question: How can we be sure in another 40 years we won't
find ourselves in a United States of Europe? Because it is up to us. We
saw in the films that we as a country are not in the euro, we as a
country are not in Schengen. I don't think you take control by leaving
the EU. I think you lose control by losing your seat at the table, by
allowing other countries put taxes on us. You lose control by hurting
our economy, by hurting goods, by hurting services. We at the moment
make the EU work for us. We are in charge of the pound, interest rates,
taxes, healthcare, education, spending. We make these decisions in
the House of Commons or the Scottish Parliament. Europe doesn't tell us
what to do. We make those decisions. We make decisions over when and if
our soldiers go to war. We make these decisions. We also because we
are part of the biggest free trading bloc in the UK have the highest
number of Brits in employment in Britain in our nation's history.
That's what we would lose if we left.
APPLAUSE. That really is an extraordinary claim. The truth is
that 60% of our rules and regulations come from the European
Union. That is a lie. And ALL TALK AT ONCE.
One at a time. I'm told you can't do this, you can't do this because of
the EU. There are five presidents of the EU. Can anyone name them? And
did anyone vote for them? You don't vote, for them because you are not
allowed to vote for them, and you can't kick them out either.
APPLAUSE. The problem is that in the EU there are 10,000 officials,
nearly twice the number of people in this room by the way, who earn more
than the UK Prime Minister. And you're paying for them. And that
gravy train is continuing. So we, we, Britain, have voted against
Europe 70 times. And 70 times we have been outvoted. So how does that
mean we have any influence in Europe?
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE. Frances? I think we've already heard Britain is
a sovereign state, and we should be proud of that. We do control our
taxes, our public spending, all these other decisions that sometimes
Westminster politicians like to blame on Brussels. We do make those
decisions. But where you have a fantastic market that gives you real
bargaining power in the global economy of 500 million people on
which 3 million jobs depend, then of course you should have fair rules
that everybody has to play by. Again, I keep hearing about
regulation, these are our rights. This is about treating workers
fairly. We should be proud of that. I will be honest with you, I'm proud
of being British, but there is nothing patriotic about a lack of a
plan as to what even would happen if we came out? There is nothing
patriotic about putting people's jobs at risk.
APPLAUSE. I think we've heard enough from Project Fear over the last
couple of weeks, I really do. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE. I will give
you one statistic. They go on and on about the single market. Let me tell
you, since the dawn of the single market, which I remember reporting,
there have been, 1992 it January 1993, there've been 27 countries
that have done better than the United Kingdom at exporting goods
into the single market, they include India, China and America. The best
place for us is to be out of this morass, this supreme legal system.
Sadiq Khan is completely wrong. The European Court of Justice is the
supreme legal authority in our country. From which, and he knows
that because he's a lawyer, he would not deny that. Deny it. You would
not deny it. The European Court of Justice is acquiring steadily more
powers. Under the Lisbon Treaty the EU expended by about 45 new areas of
competence, and the European Court of Justice... And a United States
state of Europe? Adjudicating in home affairs matters of deporting
terrorist suspects, divorce laws, nothing to do with the idea of a
single market. And the United States of Europe. Boris, I have to leave
you because you've gone on, a United States of Europe in 40 years, yes or
no Remember what John Major said about the single currency. He said
it had all the quaintness and implausibility of a rain dance and
look where it is now, destroying jobs across the European Union.
Let's get out of this thing and we'll do better, creating free trade
deals. Vote Leave and take back control.
APPLAUSE. Ruth? So that's a no then. Even Boris Johnson doesn't think
there is going to be a United States of Europe in 40 years' time. There's
one now. I need to pick up on something Andrea said. I can't let
it stand you make a blatant untruth. 60% of our laws is made in Europe,
she says. It is simply not true. 13% of our laws, according to the
independent House of Commons library, that number is 13%. In the
last five-year Parliament it was four. Four bills out of 121 that
came out of Europe. I think there is a real question here that you're
being asked to make a decision that's irreversible. We wake up on
Friday, we don't like it and it was sold on a lie. They lie about the
cost of Europe, about Turkey's entry to Europe. They lie about the
European Army, because we've got a veto on that. They've lied about
that too and it is not good enough. You deserve the truth, you deserve
the truth. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE. Gisela? You
do deserve the truth. If the Prime Minister is refusing to say that he
would exercise his veto over Turkey, what do you this I he's going to
veto? Let's be clear about the United States of Europe, which
Douglas addresses. Those countries in the eurozone will have to
integrate more deeply. And in a sense we have already left, because
they have to do things in their own interests and we are purely
peripheral. So the best thing to do is come back and take control. The
other thing, there are a number of things out there which the European
Commission is holding back until after the referendum. Tax
identification number, European-wide. We have not vetoed
that. Why do you think that's going to happen?
APPLAUSE. Can I just say... Can I say very proudly that I choose to
work with the EU to fight climate change. I choose to work with the EU
to fix air quality. I choose to work good EU to deal with the refugee
crisis. I choose to work with the EU to fight terrorism and organised
crime. I choose to work with the EU to fight tax evasion. Let me tell
you what else. One of the most important jobs I have as Mayor of
London is to keep our city safe. In July 2005 our city was under attack.
On 7th July is terrorists were successful. 52 Londoners died. On
21st July, they weren't. All the men were arrested except for one. He
fled our country and went to Italy. Before the European Arrest Warrant,
he would have been there for years and years and years, like Costa del
Sol. What happened? He fled here in July, he was brought back in
September. He is serving 40 years in prison for terrorism. Justice
delivered by the European Union. CHEERING.
APPLAUSE. Our second question tonight, our final question from the
floor, is from Alex. Alex Trembath is supporting the Remain side. Can
we have your question, please? Is it a coincidence that the longest
period of peace in European history has happened at the same time as the
emergence of the European Union? CHEERING AND APPLAUSE. Gisela
Stuart? The post-World War II deal was to fold. The Common Market was
supposed to provide economic stability. NATO was supposed to
provide military stability. APPLAUSE. What we've got now is that
the European Union is not keeping up with the deal. It is creating
unemployment in Greece. It is outsourcing its border control to
Turkey. It is undermining NATO by trying to duplicate the same
structures. Just to quote the former head of Interpol, Ronald Noble, he
said the EU border system is like hanging a sign welcoming in
terrorists to Europe. It is making us insecure rather than making us
securer. APPLAUSE. Ruth? Alex, a short answer
is no, there is no coincidence that we've been more or less at peace.
The other side have said throughout this debate they don't like experts,
but when it comes to keeping our country safe and secure, I want to
listen to the experts, so when the head of GCHQ says we are safer in
the EU, I listen. When five former NATO chiefs say we are safer in the
EU, I listen. When the head of your o poll, a Brit, says we are safer in
the EU, I listen. When the head of MI5 and MI6 says we are safer in the
EU, I listen. When all all of our major allies - America, Canada, all
of our major allies - America, Canada, Australia and New Zealand -
say we are safer in the EU, I listen. And if it comes to a choice,
if it comes to a choice of listening to all of these people, even if they
are experts, or listening to these three about who keeps my family
safe, I'm going to vote for them every day of the week and twice on a
Sunday. Don't risk it. APPLAUSE. Andrea? Let's be clear
about this. The UK has always benefitted from being a founder
member of NATO. We have one of the few permanent seats on the UN
Security Council. We are one of the ity Council. We are one of the five
Is for -- one of the five eyes for intelligence. We share it across the
world with other English-speaking nations. Of course we co-operate
with the European Union and we will continue to do so. But Field Marshal
Lord Guthrie, Chief of the General Staff, General Sir Mike rose,
commander of UN forces in Bosnia, Major General Julian Thompson,
marine commander of the Falkland, they say that UK security rests on
NATO co-operation, not on the EU. Lord givery says many European
politicians like to say that it was the EU that made everything
peaceful. It was not. It was the leadership of the Americans.
APPLAUSE.. Frances? I want to return to Alex's question, because this is
not just about history. I want to bring it closer to home. Many trade
unionists and other campaigners in Britain and Ireland worked together
for many years to support the peace process in Northern Ireland. And it
took a lot of hard work. We've supported the good Friday agreement
ever since. The wonderful thing is that people can come from different
traditions, come from different communities, but they see themselves
as common citizens of the EU. The Irish Prime Minister has said that
if we come out of the EU, there will have to be border controls. Let me
tell you, the way that is seen in Belfast and Derry, I really worry
for our future. APPLAUSE. This is not the time to be
building... We should be building bridges between people, not walls.
APPLAUSE. For the sake of the Irish, vote to stay in. Boris? I believe,
alas, the EU is going in totally the wrong direction. It is a mistake for
it to try to take on this defence component and try to evolve into a
United States of Europe in the way that it is. I remember when the EU
was given the task of trying to sort out the tragedy in the Balkans. You
will remember what was happening in Bosnia. The EU was mandated
specifically for four years, the EU was given that diplomatic and indeed
military task. It was a disaster, about 1 million people died. It was
only solved when the Americans came in. I was there. I remember
reporting it. We saw what happened when the Dayton accords and NATO
finally asserted primacy. That was the right thing. I do worry about
our security on the streets of this city to get back to a point that was
made earlier. It is absolutely extraordinary that the the European
Court of Justice, not the Court of Human Rights in Strasbourg, but the
Court of Justice in Luxembourg is telling our Home Secretary she may
not support people with serious criminal convictions to other
European countries, or indeed people who've been arrested for serious
terrorist offences, such as Abu Hamza's daughter-in-law law. I think
it is absolutely amazing, and how the Remain side have the cheek to
come and tell us that we improve our security by staying in this
organisation, I do not understand. The best way forward is to keep the
European Arrest Warrant inter-Governmentally. Thank you.
Andrea and Boris talks about our allies, talked about Nato. It's not
a choice between the EU and Nato or between the EU and our allies, we
can still have a special relationship with the USA and be in
Nato. Which of our allies, USA, Canada, New Zealand, Australia,
which of the Nato members is encouraging us to leave the EU or
says it's in our interests? Name one. Just one. Name us one. USA?
Canada? News zealed? Australia? One of the Nato countries? All of them
are saying we're safer together. All of them are also saying as long as
the European Union keeps trying to copy what Nato does, if the
countries across Europe are not paying their 2% of the GDP, which is
the Nato contribution, we will be weakening it. Stay and fight, don't
quit. Let's stay and persuade our allies to pay. Don't be a quitter.
Be proud. We can do it. We heard earlier, that the Prime Minister was
meant to have got a deal. That deal amounted to absolutely nothing. It's
temporary. So when you've had the most serious renegotiation attempts
by a British Prime Minister, certainly since I've been in
politics, and the best he got out was nothing, how do you think you're
going to change it after you have voted to Remain? There's a dangerer
in remaining, vote Leave. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
I think Boris maybe misjudged this panel by talking about the Balkans.
What he probably doesn't know is I was sent to the Balkans as a
reporter. I have never been more proud in my life than watching
British troops with a Union Jack on their arm to see them pulling their
weight and helping in the European Union. It's what caused me to join
up and serve. So I think I'm the only one on this panel who's worn
the Queen's uniform. While I have the greatest respect for the retired
general Lord Guthrie, the greatest of respect for him and with the
greatest of respect for him, I would gently remind the other side of this
debate that as a retired general, he's not currently charged with the
safety and security of our nation. All those people who are currently
charged, every single one of them, an every single one of our major
allies says we are safer within the European Union. Andrea. Let's get
back to the really important question about the UK's place in the
world. Let's get back to that five president' report, the five
presidents of the European Union. The report just last year is saying
that by 2025 they want to see complete political and fiscal union
of all 28 EU member states. So we have this one, last chance to keep
our democracy, to make sure that in future, when you want to sack a
Government, you can sack it and you know that it will go, that you won't
find the very next Government that you appoint is still stuck doing the
bidding of the European Union. Let's be clear, those measures that those
five presidents wants to impose on us do include a European tax
IDification code and they do include a European army. Let's be clear -
the best way to be in charge of our own democracy is by voting Leave
this Thursday. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Sadiq. Briefly if you wo. The other side
know this. They've lost the debate on the economy. There are no
experts... Won the debate on the economy. There are no experts
backing up their case. It's lies and scaremongering. You know, and this,
and you want the British public to take a one-way leap in the dark
without a plan. You know we can feature those plans much you know
the deal we've got. We can veto any plans for integration. Oh, rubbish.
You know the rights we've got. All you want to do is talk us down. You
should know better. All right. No, we have to pause there. We've been
outvoted. Now we return for one last time to Michal
This vote is not about today or tomorrow, but about a choice that
will matter for many years to come. So let's turn to the panel to find
out what sort of Britain they would like to see. Dianne James of Ukip,
is your Britain a diminished one? President Obama says the EU
magnifies our influence. I'm not particularly interested in what
President Obama has got to say because he won't be a president of
the United States in a few months' time. I'd be more interested in what
the two contowarders for that role would be. As for the Remain camp
talking about trashing the economy, what about the 259 billion black
hole, the 34 billion the UK has got to pick up and every single time the
EU mismanages the contributions from the member states, the United
Kingdom has to pick up an element of bill. I want that 34 billion back
spent in the United Kingdom. I don't want to keep on funding the European
Union, which has effectively become a failed state.
I'm going to turn to Tim Farron. You have spoken about being passionate
about European membership, passionate about expanding the EU,
an EU army. I'm passionate about the fact that we are sat around a table
with 27 countries, 11 of which a quarter a century ago were on the
other side of the iron curtain. Six of which had nuclear weapons on
their soil pointed right here. Today they are our friends and our
neighbours. We put that at risk at our peril. This is a vote about what
kind of country we are. Are we an outward looking, decent, embracing,
tolerant country, confident of our place in the world? Or are we ins
lar? Are we small? Are we glouring across the white cliffs of Dover?
Something which is un-British. I'm voting in because I'm a patriot.
Back to the Leave side. Tony, small, inular. I respect Tim and his
opinion. I do think that we in this country, we are the oldest
Parliamentary democracy in the world. I personally think we live in
the greatest country in the world. I would love us to be 21st century,
outward looking, international, we're having this debate tonight
with all these lovely people in the capital of the world, London. But I
think we need to set ourselves free. This is where Tim and I disagree. I
honestly believe we need to set ourselves free from this rotting,
corrupt bureaucratic institution, full of men and they are mostly
men... You spoke earlier about what British women had achieved. Why
would we achieve more outside the EU? David Cameron was givening the
pure opportunity to reform and use our influence within the European
Union to reform the union. He asked for nothing and you know what, he
got nothing back. The European Union doesn't listen to us. It doesn't
have our best interests at heart. So I'm voting Leave to become a citizen
of the world, you know what the European Union is the sick man of
the economy. Before I go back to the Remain side.
You heard that long list of figures of experts, although that's a
dismissive word at the moment, that Ruth Davidson had, all those people
who believe we are safer in, shouldn't you be listening to them.
I take the view and I will say this again, that Britain will be
stronger, more secure outside of the European Union. For all the reasons
that we've heard from Gisela, Andrea and Boris this evening, because we
can take back control from the unelected and unaccountable,
bureaucrats and the institutions in Brussels that do nothing to
represent Britain. They take our money. They spend our money. They
don't account for themselves fiscally. At the same time, they are
having a corrosive influence when it comes to decision making on our
laws. Our Parliament should be sovereign and we should be
accountable to the British public. We should be able to say no to
Brussels. OK, thank you.
Caroline Lucas, the EU is on a path to future integration. Why should we
be part TV? The EU is the -- part of it? The EU is the biggest peace
project we've ever had in history. It is extraordinary that 28
countries have come together to try to solve their problems through
debate and discussion rather than bullets and bombs. It wasn't that
long ago, since that was the way in which problems were tried to be
solved here. It's been the EU that has helped to bring peace to western
Europe, bring democracy to Eastern Europe. We turn our become on that
at our peril. The biggest challenges today are by their very nature
cross-border, climate change, international trim, the refugee
crisis. We have to work cross-border in order to solve those problems.
That is about taking back control. That is why we should vote Remain.
Thank you. Thank you to everyone on this panel and the hashtag for it to
continue, the discussion is BBC debate.
Thank you very much. We began with brief opening statements. We end
with concluding statements, the other way round, Ruth Davidson first
of all for Remain. APPLAUSE
Tonight was the Leave campaign's last chance to answer your
questions, to spell out exactly what happens if we abandon the biggest
single market in the world, to show us what a Brexit Britain would
actually look like. I don't know about you, but I don't think I heard
enough to be confident that they have all the answers that you need.
And you have to be 100% sure. Because there's no going back on
Friday morning, and your decision could cost someone else their job.
Now I know that the EU isn't perfect. But the benefits far
outweigh any costs. And the Britain that I know, the Britain that I love
works with its friends and neighbours. It doesn't walk away
from them. Sadiq, Francis and I refuse to dismiss the experts. We
listen to them. The economists, the scientists, the business leaders,
the trade unions, the health professionals, they all agree that
Britain is better off in. You are better off in.
There is nothing more positive than having a stronger economy,
supporting jobs and opportunities. That's why I believe you should be
vote Remain. Thank you. CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Thank you, Ruth. Now Boris Johnson. CHEERING
At the end of this campaign, I think you'll agree, there is a very clear
choice between those on their side, who speak of nothing but fear, of
the consequences of leaving the EU and we on our side, who offer hope.
Between those who have been endlessly rubbishing our country and
running it down and those of us who believe in Britain. They say we
can't do it. We say we can. They say we have no choice but to bow down to
Brussels. We say they are woefully underestimating this country and
what it can do. If we vote Leave, we can take back
control of our borders, of huge sums of monies, ?10 billion a year net of
our tax-raising powers, of our trade policy and of our hole law-making
system, the democracy that is the foundation of our prosperity and if
we stand up for democracy, we will be speaking up for hundreds of
millions of people, around Europe, who agree with us, but who currently
have no voice. If we vote Leave, and take back control, I believe that
this Thursday can be our country's Independence Day.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE All right. All right. Please. Thank
you. Thank you. That brings the debate to an end. My hope is that
it's clarified some of the issues not only for you here but for people
at home. I'd first of all like to thank all of you who came here to
Wembley to listen to the arguments, thank you very much for listening. I
was going to say quietly, I won't say quietly, for listening so keenly
and enthusiastically to the arguments. I would like to thank all
those with Michal and those on stage with me, thank you all very much
indeed. Now, it's goodbye from the hall here, but watching all of this
has been Emily Maitlis with a wide range of guests in our spin room and
the question now is what have they made of what they've heard?
Good evening from Wembley Arena's spin room. That debate is finished
on the main stage, but this is the moment and the place that the
narrative of the night may get honed. Over the next few minutes,
we're going to bring you reaction from the nation's media
organisations, who as you see have been gathered here. They're filing
copy and column inches as the talking went on. We will be hearing
from the big beasts in both the Leave and Remain campaigns, how do
they think their teams inside the arena fared this evening? First,
though, we head to reality check, our corner where our economics
editor and Katya Adler, our Europe editor, have been digesting the
facts and figures flying around this evening. Hello. Let's go with what
stood out for you and we knew Turkey would come up and sure enough, that
was pretty centre stage. Start us off with what we know is the truth
there. We knew immigration would be a huge
debate and an emote EU one. Is it pie in the sky that Turkey will ever
join the EU? Or is it poised to join? We heard from something that
it is never going to happen. That is disingenuous, because Turkey is in
accession talks for the EU. EU. It has been in the last ten years. If
you look at the British edgecy website in Ankara it says part of
its job is to help prepare Turkey for accession. But it is nowhere
near joining. In those ten years it has hardly advanced on the talks,
and that's science and research, never mind freedom of speech and
human rights. Even if it fulfilled all the criteria, every country,
including the EU, would have a veto. What's the truth in that ?38, on
wage? On wages? The economy Remain believe is their strong suit.
Frances O'Grady made this striking claim that we would be ?38 a week
worse off if Britain leaves the European Union. The big problem for
the Remain camp on this economic debate is yes most large economic
organisations believe that in the short term at least if Britain left
the European Union there would be a short term economic hit. But Remain
made into this specific number, ?38 a week. That depends on which of the
models you look at. It is difficult to say from a forecast you can draw
out these precise numbers. That's where the public watching it think,
hang on a minute, this is only a forecast. It is about the future.
How can you be that specific? We heard this phrase ntinued throughout
the night - take back control. What's the truth about which side
can take back control? We heard from Andrea Leadsom tonight particularly,
she said this considered that within the EU we've got the freedom of
movement for EU citizens. She played the safety card, she said it was
impossible to stop EU citizens coming, even if they have a criminal
record they can come to the UK. She is correct and incorrect, you can
stop EU citizens coming from the UK. Having a criminal record isn't good
enough. You have to pose that they pose an actual risk. It is possible
to stop them coming. When you look at Remain, they argued strongly in
favour of immigration. They said the Government here, the UK Government,
has the better plan so that essential services aren't affected.
You cannot plan. With freedom of movement with EU citizens you never
know how many will apply for jobs in the UK. And growth, what do we know
about that? One striking claim was that the eurozone has only Continent
in the world with worse growth than the eurozone and the Leave camp said
that's Antarctica. That sounds good superficially, but in growth Europe
and the eurozone is doing slightly better this year and the UK and the
US. If you look at continents or parts of continents like Latin Mc,
they've been growing more slowly than the eurozone. It is this idea
of Britain being shackled to a poorry performing eurozone has been
true in the past. But there is some evidence that Europe has been
growing more quickly. This Antarctica claim is increasingly
difficult for them to execute. Thank you. There's much more expert
analysis online. And on social media. One of the moments that got
the assembled journalists excited this evening was that question, how
the UK economy will fare outside the EU. A tricky one for the Leave
campaign, with reports from economists about the risks of
leading. Let's talk to one of the leading Leave voices, Michael Gove.
Thank you Emily. I pointed out in a previous debate that many of the
people who are urging us to stay in the European Union were the same
people who got it wrong over the single currency. They made a mistake
in the past. They are making a mistake now. What was really
striking about tonight was the Leave side put forward an optimistic
can-do hopeful case which resonated with the audience. Whereas the
Remain side were concentrating very much on a pessimistic story of doing
Britain down and saying that we can't cope outside the European
Union, and if we vote to Leave we'll have war in Northern Ireland and the
NHS collapsing. They accused you not of Project Fear but. In project
Hate. Do you think the campaign went over the top on the immigration
message? Absolutely not. Sadiq Khan has said in the past it is wrong to
say that people who want migration controlled are prejudiced. You admit
that it made you shudder. Do you think it has become a turning point
where you don't want to push the immigration line too much? I am
engaged, as the Leave campaign are, with a conversation with the British
people how we can take back control of critical areas. When it comes to
migration, like Boris and Gisela, as an immigrant as she pointed out, I
believe Graylings is a good thing, but we need to be able to control
the numbers. We cannot control the numbers if we are in the European
Union. That was a point that Jeremy Corbyn made earlier this week. That
panel raised the question of the ?600,000 donation from a former BNP
member which you made clear you wanted to hand back. Not sure the
message got through to your team up there. I think Andrea Leadsom said
people have real concerns about free moment. Was has that a back for a
former BNP leader there? What's happening to the money? We are
investigating how this money arrived in the accounts. I think that it was
an 82-year-old lady who had been signed up by the BNP by her husband,
now dead, and as soon as she discovered that, she asked for her
name to be taken off. We are investigating. I don't have all the
facts in front of me. The imputation, is allegation behind
that is people who want to Vote Leave are somehow motivated by
prejudice. When you ce. When you have laugh the country ce. When you
have laugh the country - I hope more - going to vote Leave it is wrong
for the Remain campaign to try to indulge in personal attacks of that
kind. It was conspicuous on our side and the Leave side we made
optimistic arguments. We placed our faith in the British people. I fear
the Remain side were trying to suggest that people people who
believe in democracy and self-government are motivated by
prejudice. Michael Gove, thank you for joining us. These are the
headlines that voters will be reading tomorrow morning when they
wake up. That being the eve of polling day. For the Remain camp
there are bounds to be questions from journalists about the pressure
they came under on immigration in particular how you limit the numbers
coming to the UK. And specifically whether Turkey might join the EU.
Here for the Remain camp is Chuka Umunna. Good to be here. Your side
haven't managed to shut this down and that's in essence because it is,
as we saw from the embassy website, that it is Government policy that
Turkey should one day join, not now but one day. The myth of Turkey
joining the EU was exposed in that debate. Boris Johnson himself has
said it is not on the cards. For Turkey to join the European Union
you have to have the agreement of all the 28 member sates of the
European Union. I don't see that happening. On this immigration
issue, which nobody on the stage today was denying that immigration
presents challenges, but the idea that you deal with that by crashing
your economy is absolutely ludicrous proposition. What you've seen from
the Leave campaign is them saying different things to different
communities. Andrea Leadsom was asked clearly, is it not the case
that you actually want to increase immigration, you don't want to
reduce immigration? She wouldn't answer the question. The bigger
question is about taking back control. Yes. There are two things
going on here. One, Turkey itself thinks it is in line to join the EU.
So perhaps that message hasn't got through if it is not going to. And
secondly, the Home Secretary, the ECJ is telling the Home Secretary
she can't deport Abu Hamza's daughter-in-law law. Security, when
the Remain side uses it, he says, is a bogus argument. Europol is headed
up by the Brit. The Leave campaign have put out this list of 50 people
they say they have had trouble deporting. What they don't say is
130 times that number have been deported to face justice. We can
tram people who pose a threat. The Leave campaign have a points-based
system which they use in Australia, to promote immigration. They've got
no plan really on what they want to do. Of course, the big thing here is
our economy. What you saw was an incredibly passionate argument by
the Remain side on how Britain is leading in Europe in ensuring we've
got a single market that works for us, in sorting out and finalising
trade deals with other countries. Countries. Juxtapose that on the
obsession with immigration, which nobody denies is an issue... Any
regrets on how that campaign, Project Fear or Project Economy is
going, when the Chancellor is talking about dropping house prices,
raising taxes, the need for an austerity Budget? There's a huge
range of opinion from Frances O'Grady, the leader of a trade union
moment of 6 million people, from businesses, environmental groups,
sports stars saying this will be bad for our economy. It is not just bad
for our economy but we get a lot already. That's quite a positive
message. And still you have just seen Michael Gove asked to say
whether he will return the ?600,000 donation given by a former member of
the BNP, the third largest donation to the Vote Leave campaign, asked
whether they will return that... He said he is thinking about it. Chuka
Umunna, thank you. So there are little more than 48 hours remaining
for the campaigns to get their message across. Polling stations in
the referendum open on Thursday morning at 7.00am. So journalists
are getting quite a lot of attention, as you can imagine, as
the two sides vie for a favourable write-up tomorrow. What's their
verdict? Isabel Oakeshott of the Daily Mail and Steve Richard of the
Independent. What is your take on tonight? It is hard, if you know
your position and that of your paper to write anything different? It is
one figure missing from tonight's debate, and that's the Prime
Minister. It was interesting he didn't feel able to take part in a
head to head debate. Voters would have liked that. There was that
moment for the Remain side when they made the mistake I think of
mentioning his renegotiation that. Prompted a lot of jeers from the
audience, because his renegotiation throughout this campaign has been
shown to be a sham. Absolutely not. I think David Cameron made the right
call not to be here. If he had been here all we would be talking about
now is Boris Johnson versus David Cameron. I think the Remain camp
made the right call in bringing in Ruth Davidson, Sadiq Khan, two
people we haven't seen that much in the context of this debate, but on a
bit of a political roll at the moment. It felt fresher. Let's be
honest there isn't a fresh argument to be had in this debate, which has
been going on for about 28 years, but it felt fresher with those two.
Did you feel there was a win here? I know this is the pin room, where the
narrative is decided. Did you emerge from that feeling differently from
how you went on? It is always difficult as a commentator listening
to debates like this, because you hear great performances from both
sides. I want to acknowledge that Ruth Davidson on the Remain side
gave a sensational performance. I do think time and again the Remain side
has been shown to come up short on immigration. That's what I think
will get them. Future Tory leaders for Conservative there as well on
either side? That's part of the prism through which this is being
viewed. It is hard in the format where you have to be careful about
ballet setra for a person to have a decisive win in the context of that
kind of debate. I think that the surprise was the Viv asty of those
additional speakers, we haven't seen much of in the campaign. It is
coming up to 10 o'clock. The debate continues on 5Live. On BBC One, the
Ten o'clock News. From the SSE Arena, goodnight from all of us.